<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honorable Anne, Countess of Pembroke, Dorset, and Montgomery who died March 22, 1675/6, and was interred April the 14th following at Appleby in Westmorland : with some remarks on the life of that eminent lady / by the Right Reverend Father in God, Edward, Lord Bishop of Carlile.</title>
            <author>Rainbowe, Edward, 1608-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11144</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13012175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13012175</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 397:14 or 2235:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honorable Anne, Countess of Pembroke, Dorset, and Montgomery who died March 22, 1675/6, and was interred April the 14th following at Appleby in Westmorland : with some remarks on the life of that eminent lady / by the Right Reverend Father in God, Edward, Lord Bishop of Carlile.</title>
                  <author>Rainbowe, Edward, 1608-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ... and H. Broom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2235:7 is improved copy over the one at reel 397:14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Cambridge University Library, and Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pembroke, Anne Clifford Herbert, --  Countess of, 1590-1676.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At the Funeral of the Right Honorable <hi>ANNE</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Pembroke, Dorſet,</hi> and <hi>Montgomery,</hi> Who died <hi>March</hi> 22. 1675 / 6. and was Interred <hi>April</hi> the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> following at <hi>Appleby</hi> in <hi>Weſtmorland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome REMARKS On the LIFE of that Eminent LADY</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God, EDWARD Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to his moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent-Majeſty, and <hi>H. Broom</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the <hi>Weſt</hi>-end of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:150183:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150183:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached
At the Interrment of the Right Honourable <hi>Anne</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Pembroke, Dorſet</hi> and <hi>Montgomery;</hi> who died at her Caſtle of <hi>Brougham, March 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> 1675 / 6, and was buried at <hi>Appleby April 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> following.</head>
            <p>THe occaſion of our preſent meeting being to pay our duty to the Memory of the Great, and Good, <hi>Anne</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Pembroke, Dorſet,</hi> and <hi>Montgomery;</hi> whoſe earthly Reliques now lie before us. I ſought after a Text which might give me ſcope pertinently to ſpeak and recount ſuch things, of this their noble Lady, a great Pattern of Vertue, and an eminent Benefactor to her Generation; as that thereby God may be glorified in his Saint, and ſuch Honour given to her Memory, for all that was praiſe-worthy of her, that others may be inflamed with the Love of all thoſe Vertues, which gain'd Love and Eſteem to her in her life; and ſhall make precious her Memory after her Death.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore deſire that your Attentions may accompany my Meditations, while I treat on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150183:3"/>
that ſhort, but comprehenſive portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is contain'd in part of the firſt verſe of the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of the Wiſe King <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Prov. 14. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>Every wiſe Woman buildeth her Houſe.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Words are a full <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> a clear <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> and although there lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>terms</hi> ſome figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive meaning, as in all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial</hi> or <hi>Parabolical</hi> Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences there commonly doth (even throughout this Book called the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> or <hi>Parables</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi>) yet theſe words in the Text come in the plaineſt kind of Aſſertion, the moſt regular form of a Propoſition, <hi>Categori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and ſimple, open and <hi>Affirmative,</hi> and with the moſt <hi>univerſal</hi> note of Comprehenſion. So that if there be any difficulty by reaſon of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative ſenſe, it may be cleared by the full ſcope of the Text, and the buſineſs of it diſpatched, by anſwering two ſhort queſtions:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Who?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>What?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150183:3"/>1. <hi>Who</hi> it is of whom the Aſſertion in the Text is verified? And,</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What</hi> is the full ſcope of the Aſſertion?</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who,</hi> is the Subject in the <hi>Propoſition. The wiſe Woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>What</hi> it is that is aſſerted? <hi>What, To build her Houſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe being anſwered; Then the <hi>Copula,</hi> the Connexion of the parts, the truth of the Propoſition in the literal ſenſe, and alſo in the <hi>Figure</hi> will be manifeſt, and made eaſy to our Application, and ſuitable to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our preſent meeting: And ſo alſo the truth of the Propoſition will be amplified by one great inſtance, an evident Example here before us; that both the Subject of my Meditations, and of your Contemplations (what we hear and ſee) may alſo be the Subject of what we read, the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in the Text; a Woman, adorn'd with the Adjunct <hi>Wiſe;</hi> a <hi>wiſe Woman</hi> preſented to your Memory. And being ſuch, the Aſſertion that ſhe <hi>built her Houſe</hi> (in the Letter as well as in the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure) <hi>built her Houſe,</hi> that is, did all things nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary, decent and convenient for the building of it, brought the greateſt bleſſings deſirable to her Houſe, ſhall be manifeſted by many inſtances.</p>
               <p>I muſt firſt remind you that the manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the great and important truths in this Text (as in this Book of the <hi>Proverbs</hi>) is for the moſt part <hi>Figurative, Synecdochical, Allegorical,</hi> by Parables, Proverbs and Similitudes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150183:4"/>Men of the greateſt Wiſdom and Spirit, even thoſe who ſpake by the Holy Spirit, the Pen-men of the <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> have thought it fit to cloath ſuch Truths, as of themſelves are ſimple, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, with theſe kind of <hi>Rhetorical</hi> Ornaments; to draw mens more conſiderate attentions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearches, to fix the eyes of the mind more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on them. By theſe Goads and Nails, as the<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 11.</note> wiſe Preacher tells us, to rowſe up dull Affections, and to faſten the things in our mind, leaſt at any time we ſhould let them ſlip. Thus Holy <hi>Job</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> thus Holy <hi>David,</hi> as well as his wiſe Son King <hi>Solomon,</hi> opened their Mouths in <hi>Parables;</hi> nay, a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> here, our Bleſſed Saviour did open to the people his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in <hi>Parables</hi> ſo frequently, that St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 34. we are told, <hi>All theſe things ſpake Jeſus unto the multitude in Parables, and without a Parable ſpake he not unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Text then, ſhort in Words, but full in Senſe, hath no leſs than four Figurative expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the <hi>Terms,</hi> and the other which bear any <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis,</hi> or matter to make up the Propoſition have ſomthing of <hi>Scheme</hi> or Figure in them.</p>
               <p>1. The ſubject here, to whom this excellent work in the Text is aſcribed, <hi>Woman,</hi> we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to be ſo far figurative as, (to ſay no more) by a Synecdoche, under one to comprehend both Sexes (or the ſpecies;) For no doubt but what is aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here of the Woman her Act, Vertue or Duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs even in the firſt place to the other Sex, <hi>Man,</hi> Building being more properly his, the Manswork; and it may be as truly ſaid, <hi>Every wiſe man buildeth his Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150183:4"/>The Note or Enquiries here, then might be, why, here and in other places of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in this Book of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> more eſpecially, ſo many great ſayings and deeds are attributed to, or have had their inſtances in Women, in the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, whereas the ſame might be exemplified or ſaid much more of men.</p>
               <p>It were needleſs to ſpeak much of this, yet there might be ſome Reaſons given, and on this occaſion I ſhall briefly touch upon a few, Why great Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the procuring great bleſſings, have had deſignedly their inſtances in that Sex, and that the excellencies of Women have been ſo often and in all Ages recorded.</p>
               <p>One Reaſon might have been to put an Honor on that weaker Sex, leſt the proud, or more exalted nature of man ſhould undervalue, look down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deſpiſe that Sex, as too much inferior to men.</p>
               <p>For that in thoſe things wherein mans greateſt excellency conſiſts, the Soul, and its Faculties, we are told by Scripture-philoſophy, that all ſouls are equal, made ſo by God, all come out of the Hand of God with equal Faculties, and when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to God, ſhall in their degrees, be Crowned with equal Glory. All ſouls are of the ſame Kind and Order; Souls know no Sexes; when ſeperate, are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> like to the Angels, <hi>Marry not, nor are given in Marriage;</hi> In Chriſt Jeſus neither Male nor Female, all ſtand alike related to Chriſt, as they who <hi>hear and obey his Word are his Mother, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Siſter,</hi> ſtand in equality of Relation in identity of Sex. Souls I ſay in Subſtance are alike perfect, 'tis accidental that other things come, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150183:5"/>
Childhood, Age, Infirmities; Souls know nor feel ſuch things from their own pure principles; theſe flow from Union with the Body, the <hi>Craſis</hi> and Temperaments of the Elements, otherwiſe I ſay ſouls would not <hi>Pati Senium,</hi> ſouls of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are alike immortal.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Women</hi> have been the Inſtruments to convey great bleſſings to their Generations; nay, by a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was conveyed the <hi>Greateſt Bleſſing</hi> to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, our Bleſſed Saviour, for whom all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Shall call her Bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As God made the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> the Father of all mankind, without the help of a woman, and by tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing woman out of mans fleſh peopled the World, ſo God took the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> out of woman, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a man, from whence hath iſſued the Holy Seed, which hath repleniſhed the Church.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Women</hi> have given as great examples of Vertue in every kind (and in ſome kinds of Learning) as men have done.</p>
               <p>It were endleſs to inſtance, or compare, we find Women to have been adorned with as great <hi>Eulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> in Hiſtories Sacred or Profane, as men have been.</p>
               <p>Hence we find them memorable in ſo many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to them by <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Panegyrics</hi> while they were living; Celebrated by <hi>Elegies, Funeral O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> and <hi>Epitaphs</hi> when they were dead; Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, placed in the higheſt degrees of happineſs which Opinion, Fame, or Faith could give them after their death.</p>
               <p>I need not bring to witneſs the moſt Learned of the Heathen Writers, <hi>Tully, Seneca, Plutarch</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150183:5"/>
who has written a Book purpoſely of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous deeds of Women. <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> ſets out the great praiſe of <hi>Gorgonia, Baſil</hi> of <hi>Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Marcellina,</hi> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Euſtochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Marcella, Aſella,</hi> &amp;c. He, and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> directs many <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and ſome of their Books or Treatiſes to <hi>Euſtochium, Paulina, Proba</hi> and others; women pious and exerciſed in the learning which the Holy Scripture teaches. Nay, the beloved Apoſtle, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt and Divine, St. <hi>John</hi> directs his Epiſtle to a Lady; either to a particular Eminent Woman as the moſt averr; or if to the Church Catholick, as ſome would conjecture, yet under the <hi>Scheme</hi> of a Lady, a Woman.</p>
               <p>What Honourable and frequent mention do we find in the Old and New Teſtament, of Women Eminent for Prudence, Conſtancy, Courage, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and all Graces, as if the Female Spirit had had the aſcendant, and had been productive of the higheſt and moſt memorable Atchievements and Effects. Moſt Languages, and thoſe who have ſet out the greateſt things, have commonly ſhadowed and repreſented them under the Hieroglyphics, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and Scheme of a Woman.</p>
               <p>The Earth it ſelf, the four parts of it, Great Monarchies and Commonwealths, as a Great Queen or Lady. So the Scriprure frequently ſpeaks of great Cities, Daughter of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Tyre,</hi> Danghter of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> of <hi>Zion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay further, thus the Church, the Synagogue and Jewiſh, thus the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is expreſſed and repreſented; <hi>a Spotleſs Virgin, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the King's Daughter.</hi> The Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150183:6"/>
                  <hi>The wonder in Heaven, cloathed with the Sun, the Moon under her Feet, with a Crown of Stars on her Head;</hi> this a repreſentation of the Church, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh by ſome, Chriſtian by others.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, all the Virtues Intellectual, Moral, <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Juſtice;</hi> Nay, even the Theological, <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> in the import of their names, the Properties and things aſcribed to them, are repreſented under the Schemes and Figures of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Even this Wiſdom it ſelf is ſo ſet out through this whole Book of the <hi>Proverbs. Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> calls, ſhe lifts up her voice, invites by ſweet, yet Powerful Arguments the ſimple, and thoſe that lack Underſtanding, to be her Proſelytes; <hi>Say unto Wiſdom thou art my Siſter, and call <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>thy Kinſwoman.</hi> And therefore this great Action and Bleſſing in this Text figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſs'd by <hi>building the Houſe</hi> is fitly here at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to a <hi>wiſe Woman,</hi> as the ſame thing had been before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. 1. of Wiſdom it ſelf, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Figure of ſome magnificent Queen or Lady erecting ſome ſtately Fabric. <hi>Wiſdom hath build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Houſe, ſhe hath hewen out her ſeven Pillars, i. e.</hi> ſhe hath built, as all the wiſe do, with Syme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with Strength, Beauty and Order. That ſhews her a wiſe builder.</p>
               <p>And that is the Epithet or Adjunct to the VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man building in the Text, <hi>wiſe, every wiſe Woman</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſe.</hi> The word rendred from the Original, literally is the wiſe of Women, and ſo as <hi>Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> note, admits ſome Figure here, but we need not recede from our own Tranſlation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſe,</hi> the Subject is ſo denominated from the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150183:6"/>
Habit, Wiſdom, which is demonſtrated by Arts ſuitable to it, and gives the Title of <hi>Wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But neither this, nor the Habit of Wiſdom is to be taken in ſo ſtrict a ſenſe, as Philoſophers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly do, making it only one of thoſe which they call the <hi>Intellectual Habits,</hi> and to be only <hi>Speculative,</hi> and ſo define it by knowledge of all things <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane,</hi> from whence thoſe who ſtudied, and ſought after ſuch Knowledge or Wiſdom, gain'd the Title of Philoſophers, Lovers and Searchers after Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>To omit what others reſtrain it unto, who define Wiſdom to be the knowledge of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt things, and their <hi>Cauſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may ſuffice in this place, to take wiſdom in that large ſenſe, which this wiſe Author of the Book of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> doth, throughout this Book, chiefly in the beginning of it; where he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Heavenly root of the knowledge from whence the true wiſdom grows, namely, <hi>the fear of the Lord.</hi> And this imports a knowledge of God, ſuch as hath always a religious and awful fear of him joyned with it, and an endeavour to know and practiſe all things which conduce to his Worſhip and Glory, and to mans happineſs. Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is to <hi>be wiſe to Salvation.</hi> Therefore this wiſdom cannot be a ſingle, nor only a ſpeculative Habit, nor deſtitute of any of the other Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual or Moral Habits, but they all miniſter unto it as means to attain the higheſt end; God, and Happineſs: but in the firſt place it may intimate thoſe habits which more immediately perfect the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Knowledge, Prudence, Diſcretion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150183:7"/>
Sagacity, Sound Judgment</hi> and good <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> Theſe are Wiſdom's Companions, or rather Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids, always attending upon her, and after theſe all moral Virtues will <hi>vinculo ſororio,</hi> as they ſay, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly follow. Whoſo is wiſe will ſeek after all theſe, all Vertue, theſe conſtitute a wiſe Man, or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. This is the <hi>wiſe Woman</hi> in the Text.</p>
               <p>This may anſwer the firſt Queſtion, <hi>Who?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both why a Woman is here the inſtance; and who is this wiſe Woman? The Subject in the Propoſition on which is founded this Aſſertion in the Text. That <hi>ſhe buildeth her Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that brings in the ſecond Query, <hi>What?</hi> is meant by <hi>building her Houſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deſign of King <hi>Solomon</hi> in this Text, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet out the praiſe of a wiſe Woman, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Wiſdom under the Scheme and Figure of a <hi>Woman.</hi> He inſtances in that part of Wiſdom, or of Philoſophy, which is eſteemed by all Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers to be moſt proper to that Sex, namely, the Oeconomical, or what appertains to the Houſe, the well ordering of that: which although it be an equal Duty, (where the Family is complete and mixt of man and wife) belonging to the Man as well as to the Woman, yet in regard the Man's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment is commonly more abroad, and without doors, the well ordering of the Houſe ſeems to be more particularly, the Womans Office; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> is properly called the <hi>Houſe-wife,</hi> and if ſhe perform that part well, Good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery is her praiſe. And where even the chief Government of the Family is in the Woman, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet her part will be moſt within the Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150183:7"/>The Houſe is the Womans Province, her Sphear wherein ſhe is to Act, while ſhe is abroad ſhe is out of her Territories; ſhe is as a Ruler out of his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</p>
               <p>And therefore our wiſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> makes it not only a Brand of a bad Houſe-wife, but of an ill-woman, <hi>Prov. 7. 11. That her ſeet abide not in her houſe;</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes it a Character of idle Houſe-wives, 1 <hi>Tim. 5. 13. That they learntobe idle, wandring about from houſe to houſe.</hi> And he gives charge in the next verſe. <hi>Let the Woman guide the houſe;</hi> and Tit, 2. 5. <hi>That they be, as, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and Chaſt,</hi> ſo, <hi>Keepers at home.</hi> A good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife ſeems wedded to her Houſe, as well as to her Husband. Thus King <hi>Solomon</hi> may intimate in the firſt place, the Oeconomy in General of a <hi>Wiſe Woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the principal thing, and the great Honour in <hi>Oeconomy</hi> is to be the Founder and Builder of the Houſe. <hi>He who hath Builded the houſe, hath more honor then the houſe, (Heb.</hi> 3. 3.) or then any belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the houſe. So that by this manner of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the chief thing that belongs to the Houſe, the very Building of it is here attributed to the <hi>Wiſe Woman;</hi> made her part and praiſe in this Text.</p>
               <p>Therefore both theſe Terms, Houſe and Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being, as I did premiſe before, Figurative and Metaphorical, the plain ſenſe and meaning of them will be; that a wiſe (and vertuous) Woman per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the principal, the greateſt and moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing (as Building is) to the Houſe; that is, to the Family, to the Children, to the Servants, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150183:8"/>
to whomſoever, or whatſoever may be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under this <hi>Metonymy,</hi> the Notion of Houſe; chiefly <hi>viva domus,</hi> the Houſhold, as <hi>Prov. 31. 27. She looketh well to the Houſhold,</hi> or as <hi>Joſhua 24. 15. I and my Houſe,</hi> (that is, all perſons belonging to my Houſe) <hi>will ſerve the Lord.</hi> And this is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extended and comprehends all the Deſcents, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates or Clientels, as they ſay of Families; theſe are belonging to the Houſe; As the Honſe of <hi>David,</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Saul;</hi> All theſe are contain'd under that <hi>Metonymy</hi> of the Houſe.</p>
               <p>So that the Sum of what may thus be collected, is, That the wiſe Womans building her Houſe is, doing all things which belongs to good Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; the well ordering of a Family, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Treatiſe of that Science tells us, that the wiſe Matron or Mother of the Family is to the Houſe, as the Soul to the Body, and moves all under her in their ſeveral Stations, orders all things and perſons within the Houſe, and takes care for them; and all this, as by an Art, as by written Laws and Rules of Oeconomy, or good Houſewifery.</p>
               <p>And in this Text this is comprehenſively the wiſe Womans <hi>building the Houſe,</hi> well ordering of all within her Houſe, belonging to her Family in the largeſt ſenſe.</p>
               <p>There is, I confeſs, noted by ſome Interpreters, another ſenſe of the word <hi>Houſe,</hi> that which they call a <hi>Tropological,</hi> or ſome a <hi>Moral</hi> ſenſe, when the Figure is carried inwardly to the Soul and the manners, ſo that as <hi>Houſe</hi> may ſignifie firſt an Artificial and Material Houſe; and then by the <hi>Metonymy,</hi> the Oeconomical Houſe, the Family;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150183:8"/>
ſo in the <hi>Trope,</hi> they tell us of a Moral Houſe, whoſe materials are Vertue, a Spiritual Houſe, which is made up of Grace; but this I ſhall paſs by here, intending to reſume it briefly, when I ſhall come to apply the Text to the preſent occaſion.</p>
               <p>Thus you have ſeen both the Queſtions anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Who is the wiſe Woman;</hi> the Subject of the Aſſertion; and <hi>What</hi> is aſſerted, in ſaying, <hi>She buildeth her Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now remains the <hi>Copula,</hi> or Connexion of the Terms, the truth of the Aſſertion to be proved, And that, as I told you, by one great Inſtance; waving briefly the ordinary Method of Logical Proofs, by Arguments Topical or Apodictical, I ſay this ſhall be repreſented in the Inſtance here laid before you; the Remains of a great Perſonage, in whom may be comprehended all that hath been ſaid of a Woman, a wiſe Woman, applying her Wiſdom to this great End and Effect (in all the Senſes which the Letter, or Figure will bear) of building her Houſe.</p>
               <p>So that for Method's ſake, the words as they ſtand in their Natural and Proper, together with their Parabolical and Figurative ſenſe, ſhall be the Clew which ſhall lead me through all the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinths,</hi> the Paſſages and Rooms of this great <hi>Houſe,</hi> while I ſhall apply the Letter of the Text, by a Figure, to the Subject before us on this occaſion.</p>
               <p>1. At the firſt then, we ſee a <hi>Woman,</hi> which might lead us to conſider only what is <hi>Natural,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Original from what Stock ſhe came, or the <hi>Portions</hi> wherewith Nature endued her.</p>
               <p>But as to the former, I need not be her Herauld.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150183:9"/>
Her Blood flowed from the Veins of three anciently enobled Families, <hi>Cliffords, Viponts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Veſſeys;</hi> Lords and Barons in the North; and ſhe added (to her <hi>Eſcotcheons) Pembroke, Dorſet</hi> and <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Titles of three great Earldoms in the South.</p>
               <p>But as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> profeſſed, when ſpeaking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a like Argument, the praiſes of <hi>Marcella,</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, and of high Deſcent: <hi>Nihil in illa laudabo, niſi quod proprium,</hi> he would not praiſe her for any thing, but what was purely her own: So for me, let this deſerving Lady, be praiſed only by her own Atchievements. The Additions of Honour wherewith her ſelf adorn'd her Anceſtors;<note place="margin">Prov. 31. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fruits of her Hands, her own Works, theſe ſhall praiſe her in the Gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. You look at a Woman; but, one of thoſe whom Nature had bleſſed with her beſt Dowries. <hi>Mens ſana, in corpore ſano,</hi> is the ſum of Nature's gifts. She had a clear Soul ſhining through a <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> Body; her Body Durable and Healthful, her Soul Sprightful, of great Underſtanding and Judgment, faithful Memory, ready Wit.</p>
               <p>Theſe are great Advantages for Wiſdom and Vertue; and without theſe, without the aids of a healthful well-conſtituted Body, fitted to ſerve the Commands of a great Mind; ſeldom any Great and Heroick Actions can be produced. Wiſdom if it be not well ſeated, has not fit ſpace and room, nor well diſpoſed Organs; cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert, or lay out it ſelf; without Tools the beſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer, cannot finiſh any Work, nor bring it to Perfection, although never ſo well projected and begun.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150183:9"/>Her Body was a faithful Servant to her Mind; had ſerved it fourſcore and ſix Years, and was uſeful in all the diſpatches of her Will; ſhe had accuſtomed her Body to the Yoke; ſhe had train'd it up ſo well in all Vertuous Exerciſes, by her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Temperance, that ſhe had it perfectly at her Command, and wholly at the Diſcretion of her Soul. A thing not very obſervable in this Age of the World, amongſt Men or Women. The Body, the will of the Fleſh, commonly governs the Man. The Soul in moſt is drudge to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; imploys its Wit, and all its Faculties to ſerve the Intereſts and Needs of the Body, To <hi>make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Fleſh;</hi> a Delicate and Luxurious Maſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>So that, truly, if ſome <hi>Vertuoſo's</hi> had not been convinced of an extraordinary and ſublime Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in Man, (ſcarce intelligible by old Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy) and ſome gripes of Conſcience had not whiſpered, that it is immortal, capable of Eternal Bliſs or Pain, ſome of their Epicurean Wits would hardly have believed there is ſuch a thing as a Soul, in the Vulgar notion of Divines. But if they could well dreſs, had Salt to reliſh, could feed and ſatisfie the Cravings of the Body; they then did, <hi>bene ſapere,</hi> were wiſe and happy enough, as happy as Soul could wiſh: Indeed when we obſerve what care ſome of this Sex, nay, of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sex, do take about their Body; making it their whole days work, firſt to adorn, then to glut, then to recreate their Body, then to lay it aſleep; not allowing one of twenty-four hours, to ſpeak with, or pray for their Soul;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150183:10"/>
much leſs to take it to task, and imploy it in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Vertuous Exerciſes (the Meat and Drink, as neceſſary to preſerve Life in the Soul, as thoſe are in the Body;) I ſay, this Carnality might make the Vulgar believe, that although Preachers, and ſome Women talk of Souls, yet in truth, there is no ſuch thing.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>This excellent Lady then, who neglected, or ſpent ſo little Time or Pains about her Body, except it were to make it ſerviceable to her Soul; which ſhe adorned with her chief care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, may ſerve for a <hi>glaſs</hi> or <hi>Mirrour,</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that Quality, or Sex, to dreſs themſelves by her Example.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So that although nature framed her but as the Subject of this Text, a <hi>Woman;</hi> yet ſhe having a Body ſo well ordered, as well as built; a Soul en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by nature with ſuch acute Faculties, we need not doubt to give her the <hi>Adjunct,</hi> which is given to the <hi>Woman</hi> here in the Text, to call her <hi>Wiſe;</hi> to ſay that in <hi>Her</hi> the World had found, and has loſt, a wiſe, a vertuous Woman.</p>
               <p>For that's it; Vertue, which only makes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominates a <hi>Woman</hi> wiſe; wiſe and vertuous are almoſt Terms reciprocal; every wiſe woman is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and all the virtuous are Wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It was a ſtrange Queſtion for King <hi>Solomon</hi> to ask, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. 10. having had ſeven hundred wives,) <hi>Who can find a vertuous woman?</hi> And it was as ſtrange that he ſhould anſwer that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, when he was become a Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ. 7. 27. Behold this have I found, (ſaith the Preacher) counting one by one to find out the account.</hi> And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150183:10"/>
what was the ſum total, when he had caſt up his Account? Why! it is come to one, and none; <hi>one man among a thouſand have I found, but a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (a vertuous woman he means) <hi>among all theſe have I not found;</hi> and He had the full num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a thouſand, ſeven hundred Wives, three hundred Concubines.) The meaning is, that a truly Vertuous Woman was a rarity in his time, even while King <hi>Solomon</hi> was a Preacher.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But I hope the World is better ſince, <hi>better</hi> for his <hi>Preaching,</hi> but eſpecially for the Preaching of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and although the number of the wiſe and virtuous men and women be not ſo great as were to be deſired, yet, God be thanked, we want not Examples more plentiful in this looſer Age, of either Sex; and here we have one Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent before us, a <hi>Woman,</hi> who deſerved the Title of <hi>Virtuous,</hi> and therefore of <hi>Wiſe;</hi> a wiſe and virtuous Woman.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to demonſtrate this rarely ennobled Woman to have deſerved this greateſt mark of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to have been truly Wiſe, I will not ſtray from my Text in the proof of it; but ſet forth her Wiſdom from the great <hi>Effect</hi> of Wiſdom, ſet down in this Text, under the Allegory of <hi>Building her Houſe;</hi> taking the liberty which the Scheme of the Text allows, to extend it to all which ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious a Figure comprehends; but ſtill having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the ſcope, and chief intent of the Text, That by building the Houſe, we may intend the deriving of bleſſings, moſt noble, moſt uſeful, moſt neceſſary to her Family, to her Allyes, and to the Generation wherein ſhe lived, for which,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150183:11"/>
that, and many other Generrtions may call her bleſſed.</p>
               <p>I did put you in mind before of ſeveral <hi>Houſes</hi> which the Allegory comprehends; <hi>viz.</hi> the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, or material <hi>Houſe,</hi> the Oeconomical Houſe, the Family, the Moral Houſe, whoſe materials are Virtues; and the Spiritual Houſe, built by Grace. In all theſe ſhe hath made it to appear that ſhe was a <hi>great Builder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now firſt, that this wiſe Woman declared her wiſdom in building her Houſe in a literal ſenſe, the material Houſe, I can call you all to witneſs, who have ſeen ſo many Houſes of her famous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, which Time had ruin'd, War, or ſad Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents demoliſhed, re-built by her, raiſed out of their Rubbiſh, or decays, to their former great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and beauty.</p>
               <p>To have been a great <hi>Builder</hi> (if wiſdom and diſcretion were overſeers of the Work) was in all Ages accounted an Heroick thing; ſufficient to commend the Fame and praiſe of ſuch Builders to all Poſterity.</p>
               <p>To build, importing a deſign of a great mind, ſtudying to be beneficial to Poſterity; whom Builders commonly intend to accommodate and gratifie. Thereby Princes, and the greateſt of Men, have gained to themſelves the greateſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
               <p>Certainly, none had greater Fame upon Earth than King <hi>Solomon,</hi> nor was his name exalted high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for any thing which his Wiſdom enabled him to perform, than for his Building the Temple, and his Houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150183:11"/>Thus <hi>Trajan,</hi> the beſt of the Emperours (while they were Heathen) was the greateſt Builder, the moſt renowned, the beſt beloved. 'Tis made a ſignal bleſſing, <hi>Iſa. 58. 12. To be a builder of the old waſte places, to raiſe up the Foundations of many generations, to be called the repairer of the breaches, the reſtorer of paths to dwell in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, becauſe I am recounting the praiſe of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; the firſt, as I take it, that is extolled for this in Story, was a Woman, the Babylonian <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis;</hi> to whom, for that, and her famous Acts, <note n="*" place="margin">Beroſus.</note> a Prime Hiſtorian tells us, that no Man could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be compar'd.</p>
               <p>And it was a Woman alſo who gave the Pattern to the greateſt Princes, how to build their Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with moſt Magnificence. That Monument which She called after her Husband, <hi>Mauſolus</hi> his name, had the honour to give the name to the nobleſt Monuments of Emperours, and the greateſt Princes in the World, the moſt famous of that kind ſince, being called <hi>Mauſolaea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as in all Great Actions, ſo in this of Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the End is to be conſidered; which not being wiſely done, many have erected buildings to their Folly, and their Houſes (which they deſigned for Glory) have been called by that name for want of a <hi>Wiſe Maſter-Builder</hi> to foreſee the End for which they built.</p>
               <p>As moſt of the Pompous Builders of old, thoſe vain Perſons who built their <hi>Babel,</hi> and the proud King his <hi>Babylon,</hi> to get a Name, or a vain-glory; and therefore they did, as <hi>Tully</hi> terms it, <hi>ſtruere inſanas moles,</hi> amaſs together wild and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150183:12"/>
heaps, vaſt bulks, things of more admiration than uſe.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore ſee what kind of Buildings this wiſe Woman erected, and for what end they were repaired, or built: And here we ſhall find, that <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity, Gratitude</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> were her Inciters to this Work; that all her Buildings were for God, or for the Poor, or for the Honour of her Progenitors, or the Benefit of her <hi>Poſterity:</hi> theſe were the ends which ſhe propounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to her ſelf in building.</p>
               <p>Indeed, one of the firſt things (as I was inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) which ſhe built, was (what <hi>Jacob</hi> had firſt done) a <hi>Pillar.</hi> She built a <hi>Pillar,</hi> a Monument which ſtands in the High-way, at the place where her endeared Mother and ſhe laſt parted, and took their final farewel. And as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, <hi>ſhe poured oyl upon this pillar,</hi> the oyl of Charity, pouring down then, and yearly ſince, (and that the Cruce of oyl may never fail, ordered to be always continued;) at a ſet day every year a ſum of mony, <hi>that oyl to make glad the heart of the poor;</hi> and withall to be as a precious ointment to perfume her pious Mother's Memory, that her good name, and their mutual dearneſs of Affection might be engraven, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by their Poſterity and the Poor to all generations.</p>
               <p>A good omen of a happy Builder, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Piety;</hi> the Sapphires and Agats mentioned, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54. 11.</p>
               <p>But her Buildings for Charity were larger than a Pillar; ſuch as gave <hi>Shelter</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> to the Poor. Beſides the repairs and reſtoring of an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150183:12"/>
Alms-houſe, built and endowed by her pious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> ſhe built<note place="margin">At <hi>Bearmky.</hi>
                  </note> an Alms-houſe in this Place, and made decent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion<note place="margin">Appleby.</note> for thirteen poor women, a Mother and twelve Siſters, as ſhe called them, to the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al relief of the poor and deſtitute; and that <hi>Alms</hi> and <hi>Devotion</hi> might not be ſeparated, ſhe gave al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for the Prayers of the Church to be daily adminiſtred to them.</p>
               <p>Indeed ſhe might have an eye to Charity in all her Buildings, by which ſhe did ſet the poor on work, thus curing their idleneſs, as well as ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their indigency.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Gratitude to her Anceſtors was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther End of her building, that ſhe might with ſome coſt hold up, what they with ſuch vaſt expence had founded and built.</p>
               <p>Six antient Caſtles, ample and magnificent, which her noble Anceſtors had built, and ſometimes held up with great honour to themſelves, ſecurity to their <hi>Soveraigns,</hi> and hoſpitality to their Friends and Strangers; now, by the rage of War, or Time, or Accidents, pull'd or fallen down, or made un-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitable, ſcarce one of thoſe ſix that ſhewed more than the <hi>Sceleton</hi> of an Houſe; her reviving Spirit puts life into the work, made (<hi>all theſe dry bones live</hi>) theſe ſcattered Stones come together; thoſe Ruines forſake their Rubbiſh, and lift up their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heads to their former height. A marvellous task it was which ſhe undertook, to deſign the re-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many, and ſuch great Fabricks; to rear up them, when the earthly houſe of <hi>her Tabernacle</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150183:13"/>
to ſtoop and decline; being about the ſixtieth year of her Age when ſhe began: who then could hope to finiſh? but when ſhe did conſider in her great mind, did think (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 14.) <hi>upon the ſtones, and it pitied her to ſee them in the duſt</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">One had lain 140 years de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, after the Fire had conſumed it. (<hi>Brough</hi>-Caſtle the Timber burn'd, <hi>Anno</hi> 1521.) Another 320 years, after the invading <hi>Scots</hi> had waſted it. (<hi>Pendragon</hi>-Caſtle, waſted by <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scots, Anno</hi> 1341.)</note>. Her Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (as with her hands) ſet on the work, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, cemented, finiſhed; and where others might have thought it glory enough to have been the <hi>Reſtorer</hi> of any one, ſhe laid the <hi>Top-ſtone</hi> on them all. Theſe Houſes, the End of her building them was, I ſay, Gratitude to her Anceſtors: and alſo,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Kindneſs to her Poſterity and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that they might find the bleſſing of <hi>Canaan, Houſes which they built not,</hi> accommodations ready prepared for them.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, She could not forget the main End of her building, <hi>Piety to God,</hi> in re-building, or repairing his <hi>Houſes, Churches,</hi> or <hi>Chappels.</hi> She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built, or, by repairing, reſtored ſix Houſes of her own, but of God's Houſes ſeven <note n="*" place="margin">Brougham, Nine-Kirks, Appleby, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, Maller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtang, Barden, Skipton.</note>. She had no dwelling for her ſelf, where God had not a Houſe to be worſhipped publickly, beſides private Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories in her Houſes.</p>
               <p>If now I could ſet before your eyes, or before your Imaginations, <hi>ſix Caſtles, ſeven Churches</hi> or <hi>Chappels,</hi> beſides the two <hi>Alms-houſes,</hi> and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſubſervient Buildings, which ſhe made, or made uſeful; if I could repreſent all theſe before you in one Landskip or view, you would imagine you ſaw ſomething greater than an <hi>Eſcurial:</hi> an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150183:13"/>
eighth Wonder, or ſomething more wonderful than the ſeven, which the Heathen World hath boaſted of; at leaſt more Beneficial to the world than they. Some of thoſe Wonders were (poſſibly) but Poetical; built but by fancy; all of them (as I take it) theſe great and monſtrous Buildings, were to no greater End than to make the name of the Builders Endleſs. But all this wiſe Woman's Buildings, as you ſee, were to ſome <hi>good End,</hi> were given either to <hi>Charity</hi> towards the Poor, <hi>Gratitude</hi> to her Anceſtors, <hi>Kindneſs</hi> to her Poſterity, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the Worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>As that good Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> was by his emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Succeſſor (finding his Name or Motto on ſo many Walls built by himſelf) called <hi>Parietaria,</hi> a Wall-flower, a flower (which ſeldom dyes, or eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revives) with us, a flower fragrant, and of a ſweet ſmell; ſo let the name of this Excellent Lady live, and grow, and be a fragrancy; be a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to all thoſe who ſhall poſſeſs or find Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or Charity, or the Service of God celebrated within theſe Walls, or any of them, which ſhe hath thus erected or reſtored.</p>
               <p>And thus much for this Wiſe Woman's building her material Houſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Her Family.</hi> The Allegory leads me to another Houſe worth your viewing, and that is it which ſeems moſt aim'd at in the Text; and the building of which is a greater inſtance of a Wiſe Woman than any outward building can be. This is the Oeconomical Houſe, the <hi>Building,</hi> that is to ſay, the well-ordering of a <hi>Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150183:14"/>The doing of which is a piece of ſo great Skill and Wiſdom, that Wiſe men, <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts, Aristotle</hi> himſelf has given it a place, and name of a particular Science (amongſt thoſe which are the <hi>Prudential) Oeconomy;</hi> directing in it, by as good Rules and Precepts as in any other, in any part of <hi>Moral Philoſophy.</hi> And it is indeed as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the World ſhould be well inſtructed in this, as in any other Science in the whole <hi>Circle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Mankind, which is made up of ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, could not have been ſupported, if they had been to live always ſeparate and ſingle; and not formed themſelves into Society, which ſuppoſes Government, made up of <hi>Order,</hi> and that ſuppoſes ſubordination.</p>
               <p>It is true, every particular man hath a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in himſelf; is a King in <hi>Plato</hi>'s ſenſe, hath a Body and Soul, Paſſions and Members, Words, and Thoughts under his Power and Government; <hi>Ethics, Moral Philoſophy</hi> teaches this Art of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government.</p>
               <p>But man being intended for Society, the firſt rank of that is a <hi>Family;</hi> 'tis the Science of <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi> teaches to rule that well, to <hi>Order</hi> the houſe. Now in this Houſe the Subordinate in it are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Children, Servants, and Retainers; And to continue the Allegory, the Building of this Houſe is the Governing, the Providing for, the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Maintaining, the Ordering and Well-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plining of theſe by certain Rules, of which Wiſe men have ſaid much in their Books; and of which we find much in the Book of God; this Book of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> moſt copiouſly. So alſo in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150183:14"/>
(<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. ch. 6. <hi>Coll. 3. 4. Tit.</hi> 2. and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedly in ſeveral other Places.</p>
               <p>And certainly good Oeconomy, or right order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Family, is a noble and profitable Art, to be learned by much prudent thinking and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Although the World think little of it, and few ſtudy this Art, deeming themſelves naturally wiſe enough, or inſpired with the knowledg of this; if they have means and conveniencies to ſet up a Family, they govern it by rote, not by Rule; if they be rich enough to ſupport it, they mind not to govern (morally) otherwiſe than by <hi>Had-I-wiſt,</hi> hand over head, as things fall out contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently; I mean as to the <hi>Moral,</hi> or Religious part of governing, live like (<hi>Nomades</hi> or <hi>Tartars</hi>) thoſe that live at random.</p>
               <p>Now this neglect of Government in a Family, breeds the greateſt miſchief in the World; ſpreads diſorder over the face of the Earth. Families ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered will make ill-governed Cities, and theſe miſ-govern'd, will fill the whole Common-wealth and Kingdom with diſorder and confuſion; Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies being the firſt Principles of Bodies publick, the Seminaries which ſtock Cities, out of which Kingdoms and Common-wealths do grow.</p>
               <p>There is no greater cauſe of decay to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, nor bane to the Church, than want of Diſcipline and good Order in Families, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to one branch of them; miſ-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ill-educating of Children, who are the firſt Elements of Cities and Kingdoms: Undiſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plined and bad Children, will hardly make good men, nor honeſt <hi>Common-wealths-men,</hi> nor well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>principled
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150183:15"/>
Subjects, of which a Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Train up a child then in the fear of the Lord,</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a new Veſſel with wholſom Liquor; if they at firſt are not ſeaſon'd with good, or if bad prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples be infus'd into them, they will (without extraordinary Grace do renew them) carry a tang, and ill ſavour to old age. Miſ-government in this part of the Family, vitious humours in Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, like a fault in the firſt concoction, breeds an exuberancy of habits, ſeldom to be corrected and purged out.</p>
               <p>Now this part of Family-Government chiefly belongs to Women; who, when mens occaſions call them out, are commonly fix'd to the Houſe, as Intelligences to their Sphear; who, although the man, as the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> directs the general mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all; yet the particular and regular inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Children are commonly formed by the Woman; and if ſhe be indeed intelligent and Wiſe, none can do it better. Children well inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in <hi>Gynaeceo,</hi> as plants well ordered in the Nurſery, will thrive, and proſper, and fill the World with good fruit.</p>
               <p>Now this Houſe, the Family, and the well-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of it in all the members (which is indeed the building of it) this Wiſe Woman did perform with greateſt Providence and Prudence. Her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which were but two <note n="*" place="margin">Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Thanet,</hi> and <hi>Iſabella</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton.</hi>
                  </note>, that grew up to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect age; ſhe built them up in the <hi>nurture and fear of the Lord;</hi> ſeaſon'd them with ſound Principles of Religion, as was ſufficiently evident to thoſe who have known them, and their conſtancy to the true
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150183:15"/>
Religion, in which they were trained up; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Children the ſame Principles which they had ſucked with their Mothers milk.</p>
               <p>This excellent Lady had, I ſay, but two to build on; but God did ſo bleſs them, even in the ſight of their Mother, that ſhe ſaw them arrive at the pitch and praiſe of Wiſe Women. And by their iſſue they gave her Pregnant hopes, that they would build up, or keep up the Houſe of her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled Family, like <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi> which two did build the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So that her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and her Childrens Children, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, did ſpring up, crave, and receive her Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and ſhall always call her Bleſſed, who hath intayled ſuch Bleſſings upon them, by her Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Piety, and Providence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 22.</p>
               <p>Next, As to her Servants domeſtick, ſhe well knew that they were <hi>pars domûs;</hi> and how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a part of the Houſe the Servants are, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be kept tight, ſuſtain'd, and carefully to be held up, if in decay, repaired; and therefore this part of her Houſe ſhe was always building or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing by the hand of her bounty, as well as by good and Religious Order in her Family. Indeed ſhe looked on ſome (and poſſibly on ſome of the meaner ſort of her truſty Servants, whoſe Offices might occaſion their nearer attendance) to be ſuch as <hi>Seneca</hi> allows them to be, <hi>humiles amici,</hi> Good Servants are humble Friends. As <hi>Friends</hi> in no ill nor inſignificant complement, ſtyle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>humble Servants</hi> to their Friend, true Friends being willing to ſtoop to the meaneſt offices of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, when their Friends need requires it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150183:16"/>
as many great and wiſe Governours of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies have been obſerved to do, in certain ſeaſons to condeſcend, let down themſelves and their ſtate, by taking up their diſcreeter Servants, into ſome degree of <hi>Familiarity</hi> with them; ſo, I ſay, this Heroick Lady would, (beſides the neceſſary diſcourſing with them about her Affairs) divert her ſelf by familiar converſation with her ſervants; in which they were ſure (beſides other gains from her bountiful hands) to gain from the words of her mouth ſomething of Remarque; whether pleaſant or profitable, yet very memorable for ſome or other occaſion of life. So well did ſhe obſerve the Wiſe man's Caution, <hi>Ecceſiaſticus,</hi> 4. 30. <hi>Be not a Lion in thy houſe;</hi> intimating that ſome are always in rage, and brawl, and fright their Family from their preſence; her Pleaſantneſs and Affability made their very addreſſes a great part of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</p>
               <p>It was indeed obſervable, that although ſhe clothed her ſelf in humble and mean attire, yet like the wiſe and vertuous Woman, <hi>Prov. 31. 21. She clothed her houſhold with ſcarlet;</hi> her allowance and gifts were ſo bountiful, and ſo frequent to them, that they might afford to clothe themſelves in ſuch Garb, as beſt became the ſervants of ſo great and ſo good a Miſtris. And ſome of the Wiſe have thought it a great Errour, and againſt the Rules of Oeconomics, to be niggardly to good Servants, to grow richer by ſuch a thrift as makes the Servant's back bare, or belly empty, to fill the Maſter's Purſe.</p>
               <p>But although in this ſhe did follow the pattern
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150183:16"/>
given to all the Wiſe, <hi>Prov. 31. 15. Give meat to her houſhold,</hi> and in ſuch a plenty, that Hoſpitality and Charity might have their portion with them; while ſhe her ſelf was contented with any pittance, little in quantity, (but enough to keep life and Soul together, as we ſay) <hi>Viands</hi> not coſtly or rare, not far fetch'd and dear bought, but ſuch as were at hand, parable and cheap. Yet here I may be bold to tell you ſomething to wonder at; That ſhe much neglected, and treated very harſhly one Servant, and a very Antient one, who ſerved her from her Cradle, from her Birth, very faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, according to her mind; which ill uſage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Menial Servants, as well as her Friends and Children, much repined at. And who this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant was, I have named before. <hi>It was her body,</hi> who, as I ſaid, was a Servant moſt obſequious to her Mind, and ſerved her fourſcore and ſix years.</p>
               <p>It will be held ſcarce credible to ſay, but it is a truth to averr, that the Miſtris of this Family was dieted more ſparingly, and I believe, many times more homely, and clad more courſly and cheaply than moſt of the Servants in her Houſe; her Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity and Humility was ſeen in nothing more, than (if I may ſo allude to <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 23.) in <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting of the body, not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the Fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether it were by long cuſtom, to prove with how little Nature may be content; and that, if the Appetite can be ſatisfied, the Body may be fed with what is moſt common and cheap. She taught us that Hunger and Health ſeek not Delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies nor Fulneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150183:17"/>O that thoſe who think they cannot live, except they <hi>fare deliciouſly every day,</hi> would but make trial one year, how they may preſerve their own health, and ſave their poor brethren from ſtarving (by hunger or nakedneſs) out of thoſe ſuperfluities and ſurfeits, by which they deſtroy themſelves. That thoſe who clothe themſelves in Purple (beyond what their ſtation or eſtate requires) would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into more particulars than I can yet inform them, of this great Ladies Abſtinencies and humble Attire, and how ſucceſsful they were to her long Life, with Health and Reputation.</p>
               <p>Some Texts out of this Book of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> the Parable of <hi>Dives,</hi> and even this Ladies Example, might ſupply the defective Application of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; reform or ſhame Gluttony, cauſe vain Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry to impoſe ſumptuary Laws to it ſelf, ſit content with home-bred fare, home-growing, and home-ſpun manufacture, and not run to <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Perſia,</hi> to fetch <hi>form</hi> or <hi>matter</hi> for their Pride.</p>
               <p>This opulent Lady might, if ſhe had pleaſed, have fetched from far, and at the deareſt rates, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the fleſh,</hi> the Back or Belly, but her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt appetite was after Wiſdom, and ſhe knew as well as <hi>Seneca,</hi> that <hi>Corpora in ſagina, animae in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 88.</note> that in a fatted Body, commonly dwells a lean, and ſtarved Soul; and had heard of St. <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s Aphoriſm, Wiſdom is ſeldom found <hi>in terra ſuavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter viventium,</hi> it will not thrive ſo kindly in thoſe territories, where men delight to fare deliciouſly every day.</p>
               <p>We may conclude that this great Matron, who had ſuch Command over her ſelf, knew how to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150183:17"/>
Deny her ſelf; had learned our Saviour's leſſon of Self-denial; and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Affirmation (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27.) might be hers; <hi>Contundo corpus meum, I keep under my Body, and bring it into ſubjection.</hi> Theſe Abridgments were in this Lady a Mortification, which Humility and Modeſty concealed, but which Wiſdom and Reſolution did put in practiſe.</p>
               <p>I ſhould now have done with that part of Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy which reſpects her Servants, but that ſhe had another way of <hi>Building,</hi> as to them; namely, <hi>building them up in the moſt holy Faith;</hi> and alſo <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them their meat in due ſeaſon;</hi> that <hi>meat,</hi> which our Saviour told his followers would not <hi>periſh,</hi> but indure to <hi>everlaſting life;</hi> this he told them of in the ſixth Chapter of S. <hi>John,</hi> when they made ſuch haſte to find him, ſoon after he had fed them with the loaves; and by this <hi>Meat,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>periſhing,</hi> ſome Interpreters tell us, he meant <hi>his Body in the Holy Sacrament, the meat that would nouriſh them to everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſpiritual meat, this Lady wiſely took care that it might be provided for all her houſhold in due ſeaſon; that is, at the three Seaſons in the year when the Church requires it; and once more in the year, at the leaſt; beſides thoſe three great Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, ſhe made one Feſtival more, for all that were fit to be invited, or compelled (as in the Goſpel) to come to that Supper.</p>
               <p>And that all might be Fitted, and well-prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhe took care that ſeveral Books of <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> might be provided four times in the year; that every one might take their choice of ſuch Book as they had not before, by which means
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150183:18"/>
thoſe that had lived in her houſe long (and ſhe ſeldom turn'd any away) might be furniſh'd with Books of Religion and Devotion in every kind.</p>
               <p>By theſe, and more inſtances, which it were eaſie to produce, it appeared, that this Religiouſly Wiſe Lady had deliberately put on <hi>Joſhuah</hi>'s holy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>Joſh. 24. 15. I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord;</hi> and might have the <hi>Eulogy</hi> which that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Queen pronounced of the beſt ordered Family in the World, 1 <hi>Kin. 10. 8. Happy are thy men, happy are theſe thy Servants, which ſtand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually before thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Family,</hi> in this copious Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, may comprehend more than I have named; Beſides Children and Servants, Allyes, Relations, and even Friends, were in ſome ſort of her Family and Clientele. The Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> is taken for all that adhered to either Houſe. Indeed the whole Country, conſidering the freedom of her Hoſpitality, was, in this ſenſe, her Houſe; nay, even all of Quality that did paſs through the Country. It was held uncouth and almoſt an incivility, if they did not viſit this Lady, and her Houſe, which ſtood conſpicuous and open to all Commers, and her Ladiſhip known to be eaſie of acceſs to all addreſſes in that kind. And ſeldom did any come under her roof, who did not carry ſome mark and memorial of her Houſe; ſome Badge of her Friendſhip and Kindneſs: ſhe having always in ſtore ſuch things as ſhe thought fit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. She did not always conſider what was great, or what might by value make the preſent worth acceptation, or how it ſuited to the condition of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150183:18"/>
the Perſon; but what (as her pleaſant fancy ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted) might make her memorable to the perſon who was to receive it.</p>
               <p>Now for the Building, or Repairing, or Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe kinds of Houſes, of which I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; the Material, and Houſes literally taken, or her <hi>Houſhold,</hi> her Family of Children, Servants, Allyes, and the reſt, ſhe had a Providence and Fore-caſt with her ſelf, and alſo an After-caſt, as you may call it, and caſting up her expence, and conſulting with her Officers. She well underſtood and followed the advice of our Wiſe King, <hi>Prov. 24. 27. Prepare thy work without, and make it fit for thy ſelf in the Field, and afterward build thine houſe.</hi> That is, be ſure you have <hi>Materials</hi> in readineſs for Building. Now the moſt material thing to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and in readineſs, is that which provides all materials in every kind; that is, in plain Engliſh, <hi>Money;</hi> which the ſame Wiſe man tells in another place, <hi>Money anſwereth all things;</hi> all things uſeful to be prepared claim it, crave it, call for it; and, if it be preſent, it anſwers them all with ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Before ſhe began to build a Tower (to build in any kind) ſhe firſt <hi>ſat down and counted the coſt,</hi> as our Saviour intimates wiſe Builders will do; ſhe kept exact accounts weekly in Books of her own Method, and the Totals were duely ſigned with her own hand.</p>
               <p>This way of ſtrictneſs, indeed hath been ſlighted in this looſer Age, as an impertinent piece of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, in perſons of great Birth and Eſtate, but yet the total neglect of it hath not onely fruſtrated the deſigns of many, who had laid good Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150183:19"/>
for Building, and could get no higher; but hath let fall many well-built Houſes, for want of Means to hold them up; and indeed hath been the occaſion of ruin to many Noble Houſes and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; while making no reckoning of what they did or might ſpend, have brought themſelves or their Succeſſors to an eaſie and even reckoning; to have nothing left in remainder; or nothing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to ſupport and hold up the Honour of thoſe Families and Houſes which their Progenitors erected.</p>
               <p>This was wiſely fore-ſeen and prevented by this Noble Perſon, by which means ſhe was able to hold up, and inlarge her Houſes, and ſo left them and her Patrimony intire to her Poſterity, which otherwiſe might have been wholly waſted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapidated.</p>
               <p>But yet we have not taken any view of the Chief of her Houſes, the <hi>immaterial, inward Houſe</hi> of her <hi>Soul,</hi> ſo termed by <hi>Hugo,</hi> ſo by <hi>Bede;</hi> the former ſpeaks of building the <hi>Moral</hi> Fabrick by Virtue, the other the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Houſe by Grace.</p>
               <p>And here I muſt ſeriouſly profeſs my ſelf to have been perplexed in my thoughts, where to begin, and how to make an end, and in what Method to proceed.</p>
               <p>If I ſhould ſay was well furniſh'd with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials of every kind, to build up this Houſe of her Soul, that is, with all Virtues belonging to her <hi>Sex</hi> and <hi>Condition;</hi> if I ſhould ſay theſe Virtues were perfected with Divine Graces, I believe I ſhould have plenty of Witneſſes who now hear me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virtues,</hi> Intellectual, Moral, Theological, they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150183:19"/>
were conſpicuous in her Sayings, in her Doings, in her Converſation, and the manner of her Life. As to her Self, in great <hi>Humility, Modeſty, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety</hi> of <hi>Mind;</hi> as to the World, in <hi>Juſtice, Courteſie,</hi> and <hi>Beneficence;</hi> and to God, in Acts of <hi>Piety, Devotion,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> Theſe have ſo flowed, ſo crowded together, into my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that as they brake into my thoughts tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, as it were, and without <hi>Order,</hi> ſo I muſt crave your pardon and leave, if I ſhall take them up as they came, and ſpeak of ſome few of them, without that exactneſs of Order which might be thought requiſite.</p>
               <p>To have attain'd to the Title in the Text, to have been <hi>Wiſe,</hi> might (as I have intimated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) comprehend all <hi>Intellectual,</hi> nay indeed, all <hi>Moral Virtues,</hi> and <hi>Divine Graces.</hi> Whoſo is truly Wiſe, hath all theſe in ſome meaſure, or muſt uſe all diligence to have them; he muſt <hi>add to faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 5, 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>virtue; and to virtue, knowledge; and to knowledge, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, godlineſs; and to godlineſs, brotherly-kindneſs, and to brotherly-kindneſs, charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that will build for Heaven, or as St. <hi>Peter</hi> there ſpeaks, <hi>be partaker of the divine nature;</hi> or as our Saviour expreſſeth it, would <hi>take the Kingdom</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>of Heaven by violence,</hi> he muſt (<hi>addere Pelion Oſſae</hi>) accumulate, add all thoſe Virtues one to another; He that will build his hopes in Heaven, muſt be provided of all theſe materials reckon'd up by St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and when he hath cleared the ground from Bryers and Thorns, purged out Luſt, got clear from the Corruptions which is in the World
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150183:20"/>
                  <hi>through Luſt;</hi> he muſt lay the Foundation of <hi>Faith;</hi> and then muſt add <hi>Virtue, Knowledge, Temperance, Patience, &amp;c.</hi> all kinds of Virtue and Grace.</p>
               <p>I might firſt tell what advantages ſhe had for intellectual Virtues, even from Nature it ſelf, which had endowed her Soul with ſuch excellent Abilities, as made her ready to build up her ſelf in the knowledg of all things decent and praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in her Sex. She had great ſharpneſs of Wit, a faithful Memory, and deep Judgment, ſo that by the help of theſe, much Reading, and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Perſons eminent for Learning, ſhe had early gain'd a knowledg, as of the beſt things, ſo an ability to diſcourſe in all Commendable Arts and Sciences, as well as in thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Perſons of her Birth and Sex to know.</p>
               <p>She could diſcourſe with <hi>Virtuoſo's, Travellers, Scholars, Merchants, Divines, Stateſ-men,</hi> and with <hi>Good Houſwives</hi> in any kind.—Inſomuch that a Prime and Elegant Wit, well ſeen in all humane<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Donne.</hi>
                  </note> Learning, and afterwards devoted to the ſtudy of Divinity (by the encouragement and command of a Learned King, and a rare Proficient in it) is report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have ſaid of this Lady, in her younger years, to this effect; <hi>That ſhe knew well how to diſcourſe of all things, from Predeſtination, to Slea-ſilk.</hi> Meaning, that although ſhe was skilful in Houſwifry, and in ſuch things in which Women are converſant; yet her penetrating Wit ſoar'd up to pry into the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Myſteries; looking at the higheſt example of Female Wiſdom, <hi>Prov. laſt.</hi> Although ſhe knew <hi>Wool,</hi> and <hi>Flax, fine Linnen,</hi> and <hi>Silk,</hi> things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Spindle and the Diſtaff; yet (<hi>ver.</hi> 26.)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150183:20"/>
                  <hi>ſhe could open her Mouth with Wiſdom,</hi> knowledge of the beſt and higheſt things; and if this had not been moſt affected by her, <hi>Solid Wiſdom,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the beſt things, ſuch as <hi>make wiſe unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> if ſhe had ſought Fame rather than Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, poſſibly ſhe might be ranked among thoſe Wits and Learned of that Sex, of whom <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> or <hi>Plutarch,</hi> or any of the Antients, have made ſuch mention.</p>
               <p>But ſhe affected rather to ſtudy with thoſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Bereans, Acts</hi> 17. 11, 12. and <hi>thoſe honourable women</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> there ſtiles them) who <hi>ſearched the Scriptures daily;</hi> with <hi>Mary, ſhe choſe the better part,</hi> of Learning; the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Authors of ſeveral kinds of Learning, ſome of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies</hi> very abſtruſe, were not unknown unto her. She much commended one Book, <hi>William Barklay's Diſpute</hi> with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> both, as ſhe knew, of the <hi>Popiſh perſwaſion,</hi> but the former leſs <hi>Papal;</hi> and who, ſhe ſaid, had well ſtated a main Point, and oppoſed that Learned Cardinal, for giving too much power, even in <hi>Temporals,</hi> to the Pope, over Kings and Secular Princes; which, ſhe ſeem'd to think, the main thing aim'd at by the followers of that Court; to pretend a claim only to govern directly in <hi>Spirituals;</hi> but to intend chiefly (though indirectly) to hook in <hi>Temporals,</hi> and in them to gain Power, Dominion, and Tribute; Money and Rule being the Gods to which the <hi>Roman Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and their <hi>Partiſans</hi> chiefly Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>She was not ignorant of knowledg in any kind, which might make her Converſation not only <hi>uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>grave,</hi> but alſo <hi>pleaſant</hi> and <hi>delightful;</hi> which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150183:21"/>
that ſhe might better do, ſhe would frequently bring out of the rich Store-houſe of her Memory, <hi>things new and old,</hi> Sentences, or Sayings of remark, which ſhe had read or learned out of Authors, and with theſe her Walls, her Bed, her Hangings, and Furniture muſt be adorned; cauſing her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to write them in Papers, and her Maids to pin them up, that ſhe, or they, in the time of their dreſſing, or as occaſion ſerved, might remember, and make their deſcants on them. So that, though ſhe had not many Books in her Chamber, yet it was dreſſed up with the flowers of a Library.</p>
               <p>Go now, and tell the Superfinical, who diſdain the meanneſs of her Chamber and Apartments; who cannot dreſs themſelves, but in well-dreſs'd and gorgeous Rooms; let them come hither and ſee the riches of her Furniture, better than <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> if King <hi>Solomon</hi> (who had Silver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond weight, and Gold in abundance) may be Judge. The <hi>Sayings of Wiſdom,</hi> which he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines to be <hi>more precious than Rubies,</hi> theſe were ſtrewed about her Chambers, theſe were inſtead of thoſe <hi>rare Trinkets</hi> ſo much in uſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3. 20. So that you may ſafely tell, that her Furniture and Chambers were adorned with many <hi>precious Jewels,</hi> more eligible than all that glittering bravery which God threatned to take away from the <hi>haughty Daughters of Sion, Iſa.</hi> 3. 18. I will not name them, but it were worth your conſidering the particulars ſet down in five or ſix verſes of that Chapter, where the pride and vanity of thoſe <hi>women of Sion, who ſat at eaſe,</hi> and ſwam in plenty, is deſcribed, and expoſed; ſo that the Great ones of theſe times,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150183:21"/>
of either Sex, may compare, and ſee, with how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe ſuperfluities their Tiring-houſes abound, of which this great and noble Lady had neither uſe nor eſteem.</p>
               <p>It was apparent that the virtue which this Lady moſt ſtudied and practiſed was <hi>Humility.</hi> Thoſe that will build high, muſt lay their foundation low, no fitter virtue than <hi>Humility</hi> for this work, for this Builder, and for that which ſhe eſteemed her greateſt building, which was to build for Heaven.</p>
               <p>This virtue of <hi>Humility</hi> ſhined through her whole Converſation, her eaſie Reception, her Affability, the Plainneſs, as I ſaid, of her Chamber and Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo of her Apparel, her Dreſs, her Garb; ſhe was, as the Apoſtle adviſes, <hi>Cloathed with humility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>all over.</hi> Her greateſt <hi>Ornaments</hi> were thoſe of a <hi>meek and quiet ſpirit.</hi> She was (by the merit of her due Titles) in Honour <hi>three Counteſſes,</hi> but had a ſtranger ſeen her in her Chamber, he would not have thought he had ſeen <hi>one Lady,</hi> as Ladies now adays appear. Indeed you might have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeen her ſitting in the Alms-houſe (which ſhe built) among her twelve Siſters (as ſhe called them) and, as if they had been her Siſters indeed, or her Children, ſhe would ſometimes eat her Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with them, at their Alms-houſe; but you might find them often dining with her (at her Table) ſome of them every Week, all of them once a Month: and after meat, as freely and familiarly converſing with them in her Chamber, as if they had been her greateſt Gueſts. And truly the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of her Gueſts, her nobleſt <hi>Children,</hi> could not pleaſe her, if they did not viſit them, and paſs their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150183:22"/>
Salutes at her Alms-houſe, with thoſe <hi>Siſters,</hi> and the <hi>Mother,</hi> ſometimes, before they made their firſt Addreſs to her ſelf, <hi>their Mother;</hi> whoſe natural Affection was known to be great, but her <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> greater; and ſhe commonly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed her Children, coming from far to pay their Duty to her, that before they made their Addreſs to her for her Bleſſing, they ſhould take the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the poor, the Alms-women's bleſſing by the way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, although the Nice and Delicate, who look only at things after the outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, might think meanly of her Chamber, her Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements, Company, and Bodily preſence, yet of that plainneſs, (her choice, not neceſſity, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) the Sober and Wiſe had other thoughts. And indeed they might look at her Chamber, as a <hi>Temple,</hi> a <hi>Court,</hi> a <hi>Tribunal,</hi> an <hi>Almonary;</hi> a place where God was daily, nay, thrice a day, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; where almoſt every day ſome addreſſes were made from ſome of the chief of theſe parts, and ſtrangers of the beſt Quality; a <hi>Tribunal,</hi> where all ſubmitted to the Doom of her Judgment, <hi>even to the ſentence of her lips, as to an Oracle;</hi> and it were not inſignificant if I ſhould call it a <hi>Royal Burſe,</hi> or <hi>Exchequer,</hi> where variety of preſents and money flowed, and was iſſued out daily to ſome or other Objects of her Charity, Kindneſs, or Bounty.</p>
               <p>She had known greatneſs, as well as any other, being bred in the Courts, or in the Verges of the Courts, of three great Princes, who (reigning in Peace) had as much magnificence and glory as any that had ſwayed the Scepter of this Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150183:22"/>But whether ſhe lived in, or near it, ſhe was one of the Ornaments of it, and knew, when time and occaſion ſerved, to ſhine in her Sphere, and to adorn her ſelf with Ornaments, ſuch as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the Courts of Princes. But when her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward clothing was of <hi>wrought Gold,</hi> valuable in the ſight of men; her inward clothing was <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> a <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>quiet ſpirit,</hi> which God moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues; which is <hi>in the ſight of God of great price.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It was one great ſign of Humility in her ſelf, that ſhe was not Cenſorious of others, and of the Liberty which they took, and might lawfully take, in thoſe outward Garbs, to apparel themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Rank and Place; which ſhe knew they might do without affectation of Pride and Vanity.</p>
               <p>When of later times, and ſince the happy Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the King to his Court, ſhe ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in Viſitants of ſeveral Ranks, what others did perchance look at as affected and phantaſtical, ſhe would only make ſuch innocent and pleaſant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, as the parties themſelves were rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the freedom, than troubled with any ſhew of Cenſure.</p>
               <p>She was, I ſay, ſo unwilling to be Cenſorious, or to ſeem uneaſie to any of thoſe, who as ſhe thought did neceſſarily pay an obedience to <hi>Faſhion</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom;</hi> which ſhe knew was a kind of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and will Reign over the moſt, while we live under the Moon; That when a Neighbour, a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whom ſhe uſed (as ſhe commonly did all) with great Familiarity, expreſſing together with her their Joy, in diſcourſe of His Majeſties moſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150183:23"/>
glorious and happy return to his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> at <hi>White-hall,</hi> &amp; the Gallantry which at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance attended that place; the Lady wiſhed that ſhe would once more go to <hi>London,</hi> and the <hi>Court,</hi> and glut her eyes with the ſight of ſuch happy Objects, and after that give up her ſelf to her Country re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement: She ſuddenly, and pleaſantly replyed, if I ſhould go to thoſe places, now ſo full of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry and Glory, I ought to be uſed as they do ill-ſighted, or unruly Horſes, have Spectacles (or Blinkers) put before mine eyes, leſt I ſhould ſee and cenſure what I cannot competently judge of; be offended my ſelf, or give offence to others; Her meaning was thought to be, that ſhe, having taken leave of worldly glory, as to her ſelf, now unfitted for it; ought to give leave to others, to whom ſuch things, of courſe, and by the Places which they held, did belong, to enjoy their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, without her Cenſure.</p>
               <p>Her Converſation was indeed meek, affable, and gentle, her Words, according to the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Perſons in her preſence, pleaſant, or grave, always <hi>ſeaſon'd with ſalt,</hi> ſavoury, but never bitter. I had the honour to be often admitted to her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but never heard (nor have been told by others) that ſhe was invective, or cenſorious, or did uſe to ſpeak ill, or cenſoriouſly of Perſons, or Actions; but ſhe was eſpecially cautious in cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Publick Perſons, or Actions in matter of State. I was preſent when ſhe was told of the certainty of the War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and of the great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on all hands; on which Subject ſhe only ſaid, <hi>If their ſins be greater than ours, they would have the worſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150183:23"/>
                  <hi>Conſtancy</hi> was ſo known a virtue in <hi>Her,</hi> that it might vindicate the whole Sex, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary imputation.</p>
               <p>She was obſerved to be very conſtant to all her determinations, and would not eaſily vary from what ſhe had once declared to be her mind. She had that part of <hi>Prudence</hi> which ſome call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>conſultiveneſs,</hi> deliberating, and well-diſtinguiſhing what was <hi>fit,</hi> what <hi>indifferent,</hi> what was <hi>neceſſary;</hi> She uſed, as ſhe ſaid, to chew the Chud, ruminating of the next days buſineſs in her night wakings. When ſhe had once weighed the Circumſtances, and reſolved; ſhe did not like to have any after conſiderations, or be moved by them.</p>
               <p>This made her conſtant to her reſolutions, even in leſſer matters, as, the times of her removals from one of her houſes to another.</p>
               <p>She had ſix Houſes (as I have intimated) in each of which ſhe uſed, at her prefixed times, to keep her reſidence.</p>
               <p>None can call this an unſettledneſs, or humour of mutability; it was not onely, that ſhe might the better hold up, and keep in repair thoſe Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which commonly in the Owner's abſence (who is the <hi>Soul</hi> of the Houſe) turn to <hi>Carcaſſes,</hi> ready to be diſſolved, fall to ruine and duſt; But ſhe reſolved by her preſence to animate the Houſes which ſhe had built, and the Places where ſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; to <hi>diſpence</hi> and <hi>diſperſe</hi> the influences of her <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> in all the Places where her <hi>Patrimony</hi> lay, that <hi>many</hi> might be made Partakers of her comforts and kindneſs.</p>
               <p>In her frequent removals, both going and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150183:24"/>
ſhe ſtrewed her Bounty all the way. And for this end it was, (as may be charitably conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured) that ſhe ſo often removed; and that not only in the Winter ſeaſon, leſs fit for travelling; but alſo that ſhe choſe to paſs thoſe uncouth, and untrodden, thoſe mountainous, and almoſt impaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable ways; that ſhe might make the poor people and Labourers her <hi>Pioneers,</hi> who were always well rewarded for their pains; let the ſeaſon be never ſo bad, the places never ſo barren, yet we may ſay it, by way of alluſion, <hi>Pſal. 65. 11. She crowned the Seaſon with her goodneſs, and her paths dropped fatneſs, even upon the paſture of the wilderneſs;</hi> the barren mountains. If ſhe found not Mines in theſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, I am ſure the Poor found Money in good plenty, whenſoever ſhe paſſed over them.</p>
               <p>But that which I ſpeak of this for an inſtance of her <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> is a known Story in theſe parts.</p>
               <p>When about three years ſince ſhe had appointed to remove from <hi>Appleby</hi> to <hi>Brougham</hi>-Caſtle (in <hi>January</hi>) the day being very cold; a froſt, and miſty; yet much company coming (as they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally did) to attend her removals; ſhe would needs hold her reſolution, and in her paſſage out of her houſe ſhe diverted into the Chappel (as at ſuch times ſhe commonly did) and there, at or near a window, ſent up her private Prayers and Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; when immediately ſhe fell into a Swoon, and could not be recovered, until ſhe had been laid for ſome time upon a Bed, near a great fire. The Gentlemen and Neighbours who came to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her, uſed much perſwaſion, that ſhe would return to her Chamber, and not travel on ſo ſharp
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150183:24"/>
and cold a day; but ſhe having before fixed on that day, and ſo much company being come purpoſely to wait on her, <hi>ſhe would go;</hi> and although aſſoon as ſhe came to her Horſe-litter, ſhe ſwooned again, and was carried into a Chamber, as before, yet aſſoon as that Fit was over, ſhe went; and was no ſooner come to her Journeys end, (nine miles) but a ſwooning ſeized on her again; from which, being ſoon recovered, when ſome of her ſervants, and others repreſented to her, with repining, her undertaking ſuch a Journey, fore-told by divers to be ſo extremely hazardous to her Life; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>ſhe knew ſhe muſt die, and it was the ſame thing to Her to die in the way, as in her Houſe; in her Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as in her Bed;</hi> declaring a courage no leſs than the great <hi>Roman</hi> General,—<hi>Neceſſe eſt ut eam, non ut vivam;</hi> She would not acknowledge any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity why ſhe ſhould Live, but believed it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to keep firm to her Reſolution. She did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed diſcover by this, not only a <hi>Moral conſtancy,</hi> but a <hi>Chriſtian Courage,</hi> againſt the fear of death; from whence might alſo be well ſuppoſed, a Soul ready and prepared to meet Death any where, knowing what the Apoſtle had taught her, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1. That if her <hi>earthly Houſe</hi> of this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> were <hi>diſſolved,</hi> ſhe ſhould have a <hi>Building</hi> of <hi>God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Death was but a <hi>removal from one houſe to another,</hi> from a worſe houſe, to a better, <hi>an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſe to an heavenly;</hi> flitting from an Houſe built by Nature, a Tabernacle earthly and diſſoluble, to an Houſe, a firm <hi>Manſion,</hi> prepared by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> built
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150183:25"/>
by <hi>God, eternal in the Heavens;</hi> from a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> to a <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And having mention'd her <hi>Courage,</hi> I might ſhew, that although it be a Virtue, not ſo often to be found, nor expected to be found in that Sex; yet, that ſhe had it to an Heroick degree; I will ſet before you but one inſtance, which hath been brought to me by good Information.</p>
               <p>It was in the late time of Rebellion and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, when they threatned to level all degrees of men and women, and had no reſpect to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, either in Titles or in real Worth and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but did ſtudiouſly, and affectedly, ſeek to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, and pour contempt upon thoſe, chiefly, who by their Birth and Place might challenge Honour, as due to them, as Propriety and Inheritance could Intitle any to whatſoever they poſſeſſed. Having cut down Honour in its great Emblem, the <hi>Royal Oak;</hi> intending that in this our <hi>Druina,</hi> no <hi>Loyal Oak</hi> ſhould be left, none to give ſhelter to any of the <hi>Royal Branches,</hi> (although Providence confuted them literally) but as they could, and by degrees, to extirpate all the Loyal Nobility; I ſay, when they had dried up the Fountain of Honour in their King, it was too great an eye-ſore to behold the luſtre of it in his Subjects; to let any Noble, but eſpecially Loyal Blood, run in the Streams, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived their Honour from that Fountain.</p>
               <p>It was even then, that this couragious Lady da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to own her ſelf <hi>Loyal;</hi> then, when they had filled her Caſtle with Souldiers, and thoſe of fierce and phanatical ſpirits, and none more fierce than they.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150183:25"/>The Head of thoſe Locuſts, like thoſe in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, 9. 7. armed and crowned;</hi> for then every fanatical Head fancied himſelf to have, or deſerve, a <hi>Crown:</hi> They were the <hi>Saints,</hi> and they muſt <hi>Reign: Holineſs,</hi> you know, gives great pretence to govern in <hi>Temporals,</hi> as well as in <hi>Spirituals.</hi> The Head of thoſe who at that time oppreſſed this Noble Lady, was one, whom even his great<note place="margin">Harriſon.</note> Maſter himſelf, looked upon as under a Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more terribly <hi>phanatical</hi> than any in his Hoſt, terrible even to himſelf and his uſurped Power. This dreadful man quartered himſelf under the Roof of this Noble Lady; had made ſuſpitious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries, or rather declared his preſumptions, of Her ſending Aſſiſtance privately, where he was conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that <hi>Loyal Duty</hi> required, and her affection might wiſh it, if there had been means with ſafety to convey it; but being not able to make proof of that, he would needs know her opinion, and diſpute her out of her Loyalty; at a time when ſhe ſlept, and lived but at his mercy, giving her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms night and day when he liſted.</p>
               <p>If ſhe had now ſhrunk, and ſeem'd to yield to his Opinion, ſhe might pretend the Learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher's excuſe, who, diſputing with a great Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and yielding up the truth of the Cauſe, pleaded (to thoſe who upbraided him) that he had done wiſely, to be confuted by him, who had ſo many Legions, ſuch an Army to prove what he liſt, near, and at his Command. But this undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lady would not ſo eaſily yield, but would be ſuperiour in the Diſpute, having Truth and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty on her ſide, ſhe would not betray them, at
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150183:26"/>
the peril of her Life and Fortune; but boldly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, <hi>that ſhe did love the King,</hi> that ſhe would live and dye in her Loyal thoughts <hi>to the King;</hi> and ſo with her <hi>Courage</hi> dulled the edge of ſo ſharp an Adverſary, that by God's merciful reſtraint he did her no harm at that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diligence</hi> was a noted Virtue in her; her active Soul filling up all the Gaps of Time, with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing uſeful or delightful to her ſelf or others. But to undertake to deſcribe this, and her other Virtues, that is, her Life, were endleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; none could deſcribe it but her ſelf that lived it; And, indeed, by her great diligence, ſhe did deſcribe much of it; but if I ſhould tell you how much, poſſibly you would neither Credit me, nor Commend ſo much, as Admire, her. But ſhe had ſuch a deſire to know, review, and reflect, upon all the occurrences, paſſages, and actions of her Life, as thinking it an eſpecial mean <hi>to apply her heart to Wiſdom, by ſo numbring her days,</hi> that none of them might be wholly loſt.</p>
               <p>That (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> adviſed) <hi>her actions in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing might not paſs away;</hi> ſhe did caſt up the account of them, and ſee <hi>what every day had brought forth;</hi> ſhe did ſet down what was of more remark, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated, and cauſed much of it to be ſet down in Writing, in ſome certain ſeaſons, which ſhe contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be vacant from Addreſſes; judging her time to be better ſpent thus, than in that ordinary Tattle, which Cuſtom ha's taught many (of her Sex eſpecially) who have no buſineſs, and know no greater duty of Life, than to <hi>ſee</hi> and be <hi>ſeen,</hi> in formal <hi>viſits,</hi> and inſignificant <hi>parly.</hi> As if it were
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150183:26"/>
a <hi>Game</hi> to <hi>play away Time,</hi> in which all parties <hi>cheat</hi> each other, yet never feel that they are <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened</hi> of a Jewel moſt pretious and irreparable; which he that wins from another is ſure to loſe himſelf. Whatſoever kind of Cenſure others may paſs of this exactneſs of <hi>Diary</hi> as too minute and trivial a <hi>Diligence;</hi> I think we may thence charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably conclude a <hi>ſerenity of Conſcience,</hi> clear, at leaſt, from foul and preſumptuous ſins, which durſt bring all paſt actions of <hi>Life,</hi> to a <hi>Teſt,</hi> and <hi>Review.</hi> Who of a thouſand is there that can produce a thouſand witneſſes (ſuch is Conſcience) of the innocency of their Life? that can, or dare tell, even themſelves, all that they have done or ſaid, and open their own Books to <hi>riſe in Judgment</hi> for, or againſt themſelves?</p>
               <p>Oh, that we could do ſo! This were <hi>praejudicium ſummi illius Judicii,</hi> a fore-judging of our ſelves, that we might not be judged, (at leaſt) <hi>not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs, I have been informed, that after ſome reviews, theſe were laid aſide; and ſome parts of theſe <hi>Diaries</hi> were ſummed into <hi>Annals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſhe had been a moſt Critical Searcher into her own Life, ſo ſhe had been a diligent Enquirer into the Lives, Fortunes, and Characters of many of her Anceſtors for many years.</p>
               <p>Some of them ſhe hath left particularly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and the exact Annals of divers paſſages, which were moſt remarkable in her own Life, ever ſince it was wholly at her own diſpoſal; that is, ſince the Death of her laſt Lord and Husband, <hi>Philip</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> which was for the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150183:27"/>
ſpace of ſix or ſeven and twenty years.</p>
               <p>But this I will ſay, that as from this her great <hi>Diligence</hi> her Poſterity may find contentment in reading theſe abſtracts of <hi>Occurrences</hi> in her own Life; being added to her <hi>Heroick Father</hi>'s, and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mother's</hi> Lives, dictated by her ſelf; ſo, they may reap greater fruits of her <hi>Diligence,</hi> in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Honours, Deſcents, Pedigrees, Eſtates,</hi> and the <hi>Titles,</hi> and <hi>Claims</hi> of their <hi>Progenitors,</hi> to them; comprized Hiſtorically and Methodically in three Volumes of the larged ſize, and each of them three (or four) times fairly written over; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were ſaid to have been collected and digeſted in ſome part, by one, <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice.</note> or more, Learned Heads, yet they were wholly directed by her ſelf; and atteſted in the moſt parts by her own Hand.</p>
               <p>But I will not ſpend more time in preſenting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you her <hi>Perſonal Moral Virtues;</hi> any one of which ſingly might have made ſome other Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; but in <hi>Her,</hi> all, or the moſt of ſuch as might deſerve praiſe or admiration (for their degree) might have been found.</p>
               <p>Her whole Converſation was regular, a <hi>Rule</hi> (ſcarce ſubject to exception) <hi>ſtrict,</hi> and <hi>ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac'd,</hi> as to her ſelf; but <hi>benign, candid,</hi> and <hi>favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> leaving others to their Liberty.</p>
               <p>There might indeed ſeem in the opinion of ſome, many <hi>Paradoxes</hi> and <hi>Contradictions</hi> in her Life; She lived, and converſed, <hi>outwardly</hi> with the <hi>World,</hi> as eaſily as might be; yet her Guiſe <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>reflex'd,</hi> was quite as one of another World.</p>
               <p>Of an humour pleaſing to all; yet like to none;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150183:27"/>
her Dreſs, not diſliked by any, yet imitated by none. Thoſe who fed by <hi>Her,</hi> might be <hi>full,</hi> if with <hi>Her, ſtarv'd;</hi> to eat by the meaſures ſhe took to her ſelf. She was abſolute Miſtris of her <hi>Self,</hi> her <hi>Reſolutions, Actions,</hi> and <hi>Time;</hi> and yet allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>time</hi> for every purpoſe, for all <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> for any <hi>Perſons;</hi> None had acceſs but by leave, when ſhe called; but none were rejected; none muſt ſtay longer than ſhe would; yet none departed unſatisfied. Like him at the <hi>Stern,</hi> ſhe ſeem'd to do little or nothing, but indeed turn'd and ſteer'd the whole courſe of her Affairs.</p>
               <p>She ſeem'd (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10.) as <hi>poor,</hi> yet making <hi>many rich;</hi> as <hi>having nothing, yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> She had many occaſions of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> but appear'd as if <hi>ſhe ſorrowed not,</hi> and again, <hi>rejoyced as if ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced not.</hi> She had no viſible Tranſports, ſhe did <hi>uſe</hi> the <hi>World</hi> as not <hi>uſing,</hi> at leaſt, as <hi>not abuſing of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>None diſliked what ſhe did, or was, becauſe ſhe was like her ſelf in all things: <hi>ſibi conſtans, ſemper eadem,</hi> the Great, Wiſe Queen's <hi>Motto,</hi> whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in <hi>Her firſt,</hi> and <hi>that Queen's laſt years,</hi> ſhe was thought worthy of, and received, as her ſelf hath expreſly remembred. I ſay, ſhe was to her ſelf, her own Reaſon and Reſolutions, <hi>conſtant, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent,</hi> knowing that <hi>the faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſhe had been like the world, ſhe could not have liked her ſelf, nor have been ſo much appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Judicious, and Wiſe. Great Examples, and thoſe that give them, are things rare, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſeen; exempt and ſeparate from the Ages they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150183:28"/>
live in; <hi>gaz'd</hi> at while <hi>living, prais'd</hi> and <hi>admir'd</hi> when <hi>dead: Future Fame being wiſer and kinder than the preſent Opinion or Judgment of Contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are a Generation who think that none can be eminently Good, or in any degree Perfect in this world, until they go out of it; by <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſolitude,</hi> and ſequeſtring themſelves wholly from Converſe with others in it, become ſecluſe, ſhut up from common Society.</p>
               <p>I have indeed found ſome Men and Women, eminent in Zeal, wholly devoted to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> who thought it would be of <hi>great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, Religious,</hi> and <hi>Politick,</hi> if ſome kind of <hi>Proteſtant-Nunneries</hi> were allowed, and inſtituted amongſt us; for which ſome have projected Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and Rules very conſiderable, and ſome have well conſidered them; But I ſhall not interpoſe in that now.</p>
               <p>But I find Women of high eſteem, whom St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and others of the Antients, have commended for their Holineſs of Life, (ſeen in their <hi>Devotions, Abſtinencies, Charity,</hi> &amp;c.) who never were profeſſed Votaries in that kind.</p>
               <p>And when I call to mind this great Ladies exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Regularities, without affectation, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> in them; not for ſome hours, or days, or years; but even all the time that ſhe had the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Rule over her ſelf: I cannot but reflect, that <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> are more <hi>glorious,</hi> by how much they are more <hi>conſpicuous;</hi> that it is not neceſſary that Piety ſhould be leſs ſincere and intenſe, by the extenſiveneſs of it; but that it is far more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150183:28"/>
for the Generation, <hi>that our light ſhould ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men,</hi> to draw all eyes to the love and liking of <hi>Virtue,</hi> than which nothing can be more <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful,</hi> (if an Heathen Philoſopher may be Judge) if we had eyes to ſee it, or mind to underſtand it.</p>
               <p>As it is more difficult, ſo it is more praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be <hi>Good</hi> amongſt the Society of the <hi>Bad;</hi> with <hi>Lot</hi> to remain pure in <hi>Sodom;</hi> with <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court; with <hi>Noah</hi> to keep integrity, to be upright againſt the <hi>world,</hi> to be ſo in <hi>a crooked and perverſe generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly to overcome the World is more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than to fly from it. <hi>Temptations</hi> and dangers are not to be ſought for, yet he only is to be <hi>crowned</hi> that <hi>overcomes,</hi> when neceſſarily ingaged in them; rather than he that quits his <hi>Poſt</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to <hi>avoid</hi> them.</p>
               <p>I may ſay in this caſe to you, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 10.</note> his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> That if you will altogether decline the company of <hi>fornicators, covetous, extortioners,</hi> or the <hi>Idolaters of this world, then muſt ye needs go out of the world;</hi> but he doth not adviſe them, (nor I you) to do ſo. But rather (as he adviſes <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>)<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 12.</note> to be examples in <hi>Word,</hi> in <hi>Converſation,</hi> in <hi>Charity,</hi> &amp;c. that your <hi>good</hi> and <hi>chaſte converſation</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter</hi>) may win, or ſhame, or convince, and poſſibly gain, thoſe with whom we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe or affinity. <hi>For what knoweſt thou, O man, or woman,</hi> (as he ſaid a little after to Believers) <hi>but thou may'ſt ſave thy unbelieving Wife, Husband, Friend?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely, it had been great pity, great <hi>loſs</hi> to the World, to the Church, that a Perſon of this <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150183:29"/>
Character,</hi> ſhould have been a <hi>Recluſe, ſhut up as a Monial;</hi> No; rather than confine <hi>her large Soul</hi> to <hi>one Cell;</hi> let her expatiate her ſelf, and fill her ſix Houſes, and her Patrimonial Country, with her <hi>charity, piety, bounty,</hi> and <hi>good converſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 15.</note> St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith of the devout <hi>Aſella,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtrictly in <hi>Rome; In <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe turbidâ, Eremum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerat;</hi> ſo ſhe was a <hi>Nun</hi> in a <hi>Court;</hi> uſing the ſame, or greater <hi>Abſtinencies, Hours, Devotions, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Praying,</hi> and all kind of <hi>decent Regularities, more ſtrictly than they in their Cloyſters.</hi> And had ſhe been of a <hi>Church</hi> ſet upon <hi>ſeven hills,</hi> would ſhe have been with <hi>outward pomp profeſſed,</hi> and have <hi>adored him that exalts himſelf above all that is called God;</hi> ſhe ſhould have been mounted up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Canonized</hi> (for another St. <hi>Anne</hi>) and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, more deſervedly than the <hi>Saint with the Wheel,</hi> St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> whoſe Revelations ſo ill agree with S. <hi>Catharines, Madonna Tereſa,</hi> or any of thoſe, with whoſe Miracles and Praiſes, their old, or new Legends have ſo ſwell'd, and abuſed the Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of thoſe, who walk not by <hi>Faith,</hi> but live by <hi>Truſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She had built a truly <hi>Religious Houſe,</hi> (if ſuch may be deemed a <hi>Nunnery</hi>) and was a kind of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs over it, by awful over-ſight, and converſation with the Siſters, and keeping them to Religious Orders and Obſervances, (ſuch were her Rules) for more than three and twenty years; for ſo long theſe <hi>twelve Siſters</hi> and a <hi>Mother,</hi> had been her <hi>Eleemoſynaries,</hi> after her own hands had laid the foundation of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and led the whole number at firſt into it, and placed them in their ſeveral Rooms.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:150183:29"/>I have hitherto ſpoken of her <hi>bulding</hi> by her <hi>Virtues;</hi> but I am not yet come to her main <hi>Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> her <hi>Temple;</hi> that is, her <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Worſhip of God, at which ſhe daily wrought, (<hi>ſerving of God night and day</hi>) framing fitly both the outward Porches and the Body of it; compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her Body and Soul to conſtant and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Addreſſes to God; and by inward Acts of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> ceaſed not, until ſhe had finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> in her Soul, had (as to ſome good degree) <hi>perfected holineſs in the fear of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have mentioned before her outward building, or repairing the Houſes of God; a good ſign of inward Devotion, that ſhe affected not a cheap Religion, was not willing it ſhould coſt her nought; ſhe thought it not decent to repair her own Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and let God's Houſe lye waſte.</p>
               <p>But it is her inward building, of her Spiritual Houſe, which we now ſpeak of; her <hi>Faith, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Mortification, Devotion</hi> and <hi>Holineſs of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For her Religion, and profeſſing of the true Faith, ſhe did boldly, upon all occaſions, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what it was; but eſpecially upon one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable occaſion, and it was this.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time when the Sword-men uſurped Dominion over the Perſons and Eſtates of all the Loyal in the Land, they permitted their Spiritual Emiſſaries to exerciſe Dominion over their Faith; and they were buſy in Catechiſing, but whom? not Children in the Church, (no more than they cared to Baptize them there;) But they muſt Catechiſe Men and Women of all Ages and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150183:30"/>
Ranks whatſoever, in their Houſes, or where they appointed them to appear.</p>
               <p>Well, this great Lady was not more dreaded for her <hi>Loyalty,</hi> than ſuſpected for her <hi>Religion,</hi> and therefore, as they had brought her to the <hi>Touch-ſtone</hi> for the one, they muſt bring her to the Teſt, and Tryal for the other.</p>
               <p>Whether it were a Committee, with a Club of their Divines, Lay-elders, and Superintendents, over all that were appointed, I have not been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; but to gain countenance, they drew in with them ſome Miniſters of better temper, and came to her Caſtle, which had a Garriſon (no good Gueſts to her, but ſure Friends to them.) They bring her to be examined; what their Queſtions were, I have not particularly learned; onely by her Anſwer, I may ſuppoſe one in general to have been, <hi>What Faith and Religion ſhe profeſſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One might well have thought, in a Perſon of her Quality, Age, and Spirit, Diſdain at ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency ſhould have kept her from anſwering, or ſaying any thing, except in reproaching their Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, and proud Hypocriſy.</p>
               <p>But ſhe having learned another Leſſon, 1 <hi>Pet. 3. 15. To be ready always to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fear,</hi> her readineſs and meekneſs made her willing to give a reaſon of her Hope; <hi>Hope,</hi> which is built upon Faith; and ſhe told them to this, or like, Effect.</p>
               <p>That her <hi>Faith</hi> was built upon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles; that is, upon the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>Word of God,</hi> as delivered and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150183:30"/>
Expounded by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> as by Law eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe was bred in, and had imbraced; and by God's Grace would <hi>perſiſt in it to her Lives end.</hi> This general (with other more explicit) Anſwer, was ſo appoſite; delivered with ſuch firmneſs of mind, that ſome Miniſters whom they had drawn in with them, to give a colour to their preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; obſerving that this well-taught Lady had <hi>purchaſed a good degree of boldneſs in the Faith;</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, I ſay, the <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs</hi> and <hi>tryal</hi> of her <hi>Faith, more precious than Gold that periſheth,</hi> (they knew that Gold ſhe would eaſily let go, upon all occaſions, very liberally, but ſaw ſhe would hold faſt the Faith once delivered to her) they left her; one of them going out weeping, amazed, and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to find ſuch Knowledg, Conſtancy, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, in a Woman, her Faith ſo ſound, and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and mixed with ſo much Chriſtian meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Condeſcention.</p>
               <p>The reſt alſo (being no doubt, aſtoniſhed at her Underſtanding and Anſwers) left her a glorious <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> willing enough, no doubt, to have been a <hi>Martyr,</hi> and to have ſealed to the truth by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing any more fiery tryal.</p>
               <p>And ſhe was after this ſo reſolute, to ſtick to the <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in the main point of <hi>Practice,</hi> partaking of the <hi>holy Euchariſt,</hi> that when there was a kind of <hi>Interdict</hi> on the Land, a forbidding to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments according to the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> She would not, what danger ſoever might happen, communicate any other way; ſticking cloſe to the Rules and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>ſound words,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150183:31"/>
by the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> to which ſhe had always been accuſtomed, and had approved it by her own Judgment: having ſuck'd alſo, as it were, with her Mothers Milk, wholſom Inſtitutions, who train'd her up as an obedient daughter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her ſelf being alſo obſervant of thoſe Rules; and that Ladies great Piety is not only mentioned often in the <hi>Annals,</hi> which this her affectionate Daughter dictated, but alſo taken notice of by the Learned and Godly Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who dedicates one of his Practical Treatiſes to <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> the Mother of this Lady, which I the rather note, that ſome may take notice, who ſo readily follow him in doubtful Diſputations, and yet ſcruple to walk with him in his practice of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Rules of the Church.</p>
               <p>She was, I ſay, devoted to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> notwithſtanding that ſhe was compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and charitable to ſome <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> She would tell, that <hi>Her Family had furniſhed this Dioceſs with one</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vipont.</note> 
                  <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and that by her aſſiſtance an Eminent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late now living, was made a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> of which,<note place="margin">B. of <hi>W.</hi>
                  </note> and of whom ſhe would often make mention with great contentment.</p>
               <p>For her <hi>Devotion;</hi> ſome thought leſs of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had no Domeſtick Chaplain; and it was an Objection, which I knew not how to anſwer, until I was aſſured, that although ſhe had no Chaplain Menial, in her Houſe, yet ſhe had ſix Houſhold Chaplains: at every one of her Houſes the Parochial Miniſters did Officiate to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, as well as at their Cures, and they wanted
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150183:31"/>
not all due encouragements from ſo good a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troneſs.</p>
               <p>Indeed when Age had deprived her of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of her Limbs; her hearing alſo being much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, her Chamber as I intimated was her Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, a houſe of Prayer, not that the Morning and Evening Service were performed daily there, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of late, when her Hearing failed. But ſhe ſeldom ommitted, Morning and Evening, and at Noon, to offer up her private Devotions to God, and in whatſoever Poſture ſhe was, to ſend up ſome holy <hi>Ejaculations.</hi> The Pſalms for the day of the Moneth were never omitted to be read by her ſelf; or, when under ſome indiſpoſition, read to her by her Attendants. She much delighted in that holy Book, it was her Companion, and when perſons, or their affections, cannot ſo well be known by themſelves, they may be gueſſed at by their Companions.</p>
               <p>No greater Teſtimony of a Soul having her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in Heaven, then by being converſant in that Heavenly Book, which, as holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> hath well demonſtrated, is fitted for all perſons; ſuited for all occaſions: To receive comfort, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſorrow, to caſt down, or lift up the Soul with joy; to praiſe God, to expoſtulate with him, to ſtrengthen Faith, to nouriſh Hope, to ſtir up Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection; to allay Paſſion, to teach Patience, to await Gods leiſure. So that, indeed we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to this one parcel of Scripture, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes the ſcope of the inſpired Books, that it is <hi>profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, that the man of God,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150183:32"/>
(and not only ſo, but that every Godly man or woman) <hi>may be perfect, throughly furniſhed to every good work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſcarce poſſible for any to be bad, that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>reads</hi> and <hi>meditates</hi> on this Book, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be good: He that <hi>reads</hi> and <hi>digeſts,</hi> ſhall be transformed into the image of it, be acted by the ſpirit which breaths in it. No doubt the <hi>Compilers</hi> of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> had all this in their eye, when they made the reading a part of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> ſo great a <hi>portion of the Morning and Evening Service.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides this, which ſhe did commonly read her ſelf, ſhe uſually heard a large portion of Scripture read every day, as much as one of the Goſpels read every week. So that let her Body be fed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſparingly, her Soul was nouriſhed with <hi>ſound words,</hi> the words of Faith, which muſt needs give her a growth in Grace, and make a ſincere heart.</p>
               <p>She took a particular delight in one Chapter, which ſhe uſed to repeat every <hi>Lord's day</hi> in the year, and never failed to do it, it was the eighth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which ſhe had by heart (in the beſt ſenſe) had laid it up in her heart; and truly, ſhe could hardly find a better Cordial in any one Chapter in all the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Which, how comfortable, how pertinent, how uſeful it may be to any Chriſtian, in any Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who deſires with Meditation and Reflection, to peruſe it; it may be ſufficient to refer them to the ſerious <hi>reading</hi> of it, and I doubt not but they will approve this Ladie's Wiſdom and Piety, in her
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150183:32"/>
choice, and frequent application of it to her ſelf; and ſhe did ſo when Death look'd her in the face; repeating it the firſt day when her Sickneſs (which proved mortal) ſeized on her.</p>
               <p>As this might excite many Graces, <hi>Faith, Hope;</hi> ſo eſpecially, what is the proper effect of thoſe while we are on earth, <hi>Patience:</hi> and on Earth only theſe three Plants grow, <hi>Faith, Hope, Patience,</hi> though they ſend their <hi>fruit to Heaven,</hi> yet their <hi>Root</hi> is only on <hi>Earth, Faith</hi> is perfected by <hi>Viſion, Hope</hi> conſummated by <hi>Fruition;</hi> and at Heaven's gates the <hi>Patience</hi> of the Saints leaves them; no more ſufferings, pain, or grief: <hi>all tears are wiped from their eyes</hi> at the firſt glimpſe of the <hi>Beatifical Viſion:</hi> But, I ſay, in that ſelected Chapter (<hi>Rom</hi> 8.) the greateſt Emphaſis in it, is to teach Patience, either in inward afflictions of the Soul, or outward preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures on the Body, ſecuring the Soul againſt the fear of damnation, though under ſinful infirmities; and ſuſteining the Body, and outward man, though under the <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>greateſt afflictions:</hi> aſſuring, that where Patience hath <hi>endured to the utmoſt,</hi> when Patience ſhall have <hi>perfected its work,</hi> it ſhall have its <hi>reward,</hi> a <hi>Crown</hi> at the laſt.</p>
               <p>I might inlarge by particular inſtances of her Patience, in <hi>bearing,</hi> and even <hi>Taking up,</hi> ſubmiſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Croſſes which ſhe met withall; as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be imagined but one who lived ſo long in a perverſe and crooked generation, muſt meet with many croſſes in ſeveral kinds; both in regard of <hi>Publick revolutions,</hi> and <hi>Private croſs-accidents.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe ſaw, and felt great varieties, and mixture of better and worſe in both. She ſpun out almoſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150183:33"/>
the meaſure of one whole Age; and the Age wherein ſhe lived, might give her experience of the greateſt miſery, and alſo felicity in the late revolutions in theſe three Nations, that any one Age had ever ſeen. Wherein the greateſt Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and Searchers into the Methods of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, could never extricate or clear the doubts which firſt aroſe from ſeeing theſe Nations, from the top of earthly and heavenly bleſſings, thrown into the abyſs of miſery, and helliſh ſlavery; and then again, by a powerful, but gentle hand of Providence, reſtored, and raiſed up to its former proſperity and glory.</p>
               <p>Herein this Lady (as many leſs aged) <hi>Had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like the fate of</hi> Noah; ſaw the times before the Flood, which Sin brought down; weather'd out, with Patience, the time, under the Floods of War and Miſery (Faith and Providence build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her an Ark) ſhe lived to ſee the deluge of Blood, and War dried up; God, in his never to be forgotten Mercy, clearing the Skies, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Sun, and Starrs ſhine upon us again.</p>
               <p>Thoſe were times to exerciſe her Patience, in a joynt-ſtock, with others, under publick Sufferings.</p>
               <p>But ſhe had (and it may be ſeen, that ſhe well remembred then) many private trials of her Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; not only thoſe, which in Common Providence, happen to all mankind, eſpecially to the long lived, who muſt needs ſee the Funerals of Parents, and hear of the Deaths, Misfortunes (or Miſcarriages) of Huſbands Children and Friends; in all theſe, there might be work for Patience; although I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that true Chriſtian-Patience looks upon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150183:33"/>
ſuch as <hi>Corrections</hi> and <hi>Chaſtiſements;</hi> and that they are more often the Indulgences of a Father, then the ſeverity of a <hi>Judge, Corrections</hi> not <hi>Judgments.</hi> And it is one of the ſafeſt ways for any to aſſure himſelf that he is the Child of God, when he can willingly ſubmit to his ſtroak as <hi>to the Correction of a Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt the tryals of this kind, I was able to obſerve one great work of <hi>Patience,</hi> wrought out by this pious Lady.</p>
               <p>When the aſtoniſhing news was brought her, about three years ſince, from the <hi>Iſle of Garnſey,</hi> of the ſtrange and diſaſterous death of one of her dear <hi>Grand-Children,</hi> with a Lady of great Piety and Honour, and divers others, by a terrible blaſt by Gunpowder, the relation of which amazed the <hi>Court,</hi> and all that heard of it; although ſhe firſt received the news with a ſorrow, ſuppreſt by a ſilence and wonder; yet after, when ſhe heard that the Noble Lord, her Grand-ſon, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Hatton.</hi>
                  </note> been blown up out of his Chamber, (and by a wonderful Providence, being thrown upon an high Wall) that he, and two of her Grand-chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren eſcaped, without any harm; ſhe diſcovered a patient Submiſſion to the Will of God, in many Chriſtian expreſſions, which ſoon after I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from herſelf, and ſeveral times after, when ſhe was pleaſed to renew the remembrance of it, with much admiration, and acknowledgment of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret wayes of Gods Judgements, and Mercies; on which ſhe could inlarge with many heavenly expreſſions.</p>
               <p>But now Patience through all theſe experiences,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150183:34"/>
began to draw its work to perfection; which it never doth, except it dye with them, whom it hath ſupported in Life.</p>
               <p>A little before Her death, Patience, and Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and low thoughts of Her ſelf, which had been Her practice, were now Her Argument. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing frequently, with one of her neareſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, and ſeeing her, and others, paſſionatly concern'd, and buſie about her, ſhe willed them not to take ſo much pains for her, who deſerved leſs; expoſtulating, why any, her ſelf eſpecially, ſhould at any time be angry; why any of theſe outward things ſhould trouble her, who deſerved ſo little, and had been bleſſed with ſo much? By which it might appear that ſhe had brought into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection all great thoughts, ſhe had caſt down imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, &amp; every high thing, bringing into Captivity every high thought, and ſubmitting the World and her Soul to the <hi>Obedience</hi> of Chriſt; her paſſions were mortified and dead before her: So that for three or four dayes of her laſt ſickneſs, (for ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured no more) ſhe lay as if ſhe indured nothing; ſhe called for her <hi>Pſalms,</hi> which ſhe could not now, as ſhe uſually had done, read her ſelf (the greateſt Symptome of her extremity) ſhe cauſed them to be read unto her. But that Cordial of which I have ſpoken (kept, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and in her heart) this her Memory held to the laſt, this ſhe ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated: No doubt to ſecure her Soul againſt all fear of Condemnation, being now wholly Chriſts, having ſerved him in the ſpirit of her mind, and not loved to walk after the Fleſh, having (as often as ſhe affectionatly pronounced the words of this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150183:34"/>
Chapter) called in the Teſtimony of the Spirit to bear her witneſs, that ſhe deſired to be delivered from this Bondage of Corruption; into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of the Children of God; and ſo to ſtrengthen her Faith and Hope by other comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Arguments, contein'd in the reſt of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being the laſt words of Continuance, which this dying Lady ſpoke.</p>
               <p>The reſt of the time, as if it had been ſpent in Ruminating, Digeſting, and ſpeaking inwardly to her Soul, what ſhe had utter'd with broken words, ſhe lay quiet, and without much ſign of any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation; after a while in a gentle breath, ſcarce perceptible, ſhe breathed out that Soul which God had breathed into her; rendring it even to that God which gave it. So breathed her laſt, and quietly ſlept, not to be awakened again, but by the Archangel's Trumpet, when it ſhall call her to the <hi>Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus fell at laſt this goodly <hi>Building;</hi> Thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this <hi>great wiſe Woman;</hi> who while ſhe lived was the Honour of her Sex and Age, fitter for an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> than a <hi>Sermon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who having well conſidered that her laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, (how ſoon ſhe knew not) muſt be to the <hi>Houſe of Death;</hi> ſhe built her own Apartment there; the Tomb before your eyes; againſt this day, on which we are all now here met to give her Reliques Livery and Seizin, quiet poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>And while her Duſt lies ſilent in that Chamber of Death, the Monuments which ſhe had built in the Hearts of all that knew her, ſhall ſpeak loud in the ears of a profligate Generation; and tell, that in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150183:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this general Corruption, lapſed times decay, and downfal of Vertue, The thrice Illuſtrious <hi>Anne</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Pembroke, Dorſet,</hi> and <hi>Montgomery,</hi> ſtood immovable in her Integrity of Manners, Vertue, and Religion; was a well built Temple for Wiſdom, and all her train of Vertues to reſide in; is now removed and gone to inhabit a Building of God, <hi>an Houſe not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi> To which bleſſed Manſions let us all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to follow her, by treading in the ſteps of her <hi>Faith, Vertue</hi> and <hi>Patience: That having fought the good Fight, finiſhed our Courſe, and kept the Faith, we may receive the Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord, the righteous Judge ſhall give at that day to all that love his appearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Now unto the King Eternal, Immortal, the only wiſe God, be Honour and Glory for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150183:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
